<sect1 id="linguistik"><title>Sprachwissenschaftliche Aspekte von Lojban &mdash;
<foreignphrase lang="loj">bauske se casnu co lojbo </foreignphrase>
</title>

<sect2 id="sapirwhorf"><title>Whas ist die Sapir-Whorf Hypothese?</title>

<para>The Sapir-Whorf hypothesis is the notion that the language you speak
affects the way you think.  Most people who have learnt a foreign language,
or have grown up speaking two languages, will be familiar with this idea,
having found themselves thinking and speaking in one language or the other
because something is easier to say in that language.  One of the main ideas
behind the Loglan/Lojban project was to create a language which is both
highly expressive and as culturally neutral as possible, then see what
people from different cultures do with it.  To give an example, in most
European languages time and gender are very important &mdash; you can say
<quote>She goes</quote>, <quote>It went</quote>, <quote>He'll go</quote>
and so on, but just to say <quote>She/he/it go</quote>, with no particular
gender or time in mind, sounds strange.  In Chinese, on the other hand,
<wordasword>ta qu</wordasword> (he/she/it go) is perfectly normal.  In Lojban there are
plenty of words to show the time of an action, its length, how it happens
and so on &mdash; but you don't have to use any of them.  If you really
wanted to, you could say: 

<informalexample>
<literallayout><foreignphrase lang="loj">le ninmu puzuze'udi'i klama</foreignphrase>
the female-human past-long-time-distance-long-time-interval-regularly go
<quote>A long time ago, for a long time, she went regularly.</quote></literallayout>
</informalexample>

But normally you'd just say:

<informalexample>
<literallayout><foreignphrase lang="loj">klama</foreignphrase>
[someone / something] go </literallayout>
</informalexample>

</para>

<para>Notice that you can translate the first example into English
(more-or-less) but the second one just won't go into English, or most
European languages.  If you're European and this strikes you as odd, you
may have just witnessed a Sapir-Whorf effect!  Understanding the potential
for Sapir-Whorf effects may lead to better inter-cultural understanding,
promoting communication and peace.  </para>


<para>It is known that people's ideas and thought change somewhat when they
learn a foreign language.  It is not known whether this change is due to
exposure to a different culture or even just getting outside of ones own
culture.  It is also not known how much (if any) of the change is due to
the nature of the language, as opposed to the cultural associations. 
</para>


<para>The Sapir-Whorf hypothesis was important in linguistics in the 1950s,
but interest fell off partially because properly testing it was so
difficult.  Lojban is a new approach to such testing.  Obviously, if a
culture-independent language could be taught to groups of people, the
effects of language could more easily be separated from those of culture. 
</para>


<para>Unique features of Lojban remove constraints on language in the areas
of logic, ambiguity, and expressive power, opening up areas of thought that
have not been easily accessible by human language before.  Meanwhile, the
formal rigidity of the language definition allows speakers to carefully
control their expressions (and perhaps therefore their thought processes). 
This gives some measure of predictive power that can be used in designing
and preparing for actual Sapir-Whorf experiments.  </para>


<para>One of the prerequisites of a Sapir-Whorf experiment is an
international body of Lojban speakers.  We need to be able to teach Lojban
to subjects who know only their native (non-English) tongue, and we need to
know in advance the difficulties that people from each language and culture
will have in learning Lojban.  Thus, the Lojban community is actively
reaching out to speakers of languages other than English.  </para>


<para>Lojban does not need to prove or disprove the Sapir-Whorf hypothesis
in order to be successful.  However, if evidence is produced supporting the
Sapir-Whorf effect, Lojban will likely be perceived as an outstanding tool
of analytical and creative thought.  </para> </sect2>

<sect2><title>How else might Lojban be used by scientists studying language? 
</title>

<para>An artificial language (AL) is a simple model of a natural language. 
It is used for communication like natural languages, simpler, more regular,
and relatively uncontaminated by culture effects.  Unlike most natural
languages, an AL has not evolved through naturally processes of internal
change or contact with other languages.  In addition, to the extent to
which details of an AL is pre-defined, the internal structure of the
language is far better known than that of any natural language.  </para>


<para>Such a pre-definition, a language <quote role="socalled">prescription</quote>, makes an AL a
unique tool for studying the nature of language.  As people learn the
language, the way they <quote role="socalled">acquire</quote> understanding of that prescription can
tell scientists how <quote role="socalled">natural</quote> the prescribed forms are.  Actual usage of
the language can be compared to the prescription providing quantitative
data on specific patterns of usage.  As the language evolves from its
relatively pristine initial state, it may start to deviate from its
prescription.  Any such deviations will better inform researchers as to the
properties of a <quote role="socalled">natural</quote> language.  The process of language change itself
will of course be open to investigation in a way never before possible. 
Finally, the existence of a relatively complete language prescription at
the birth of the language means that a <quote role="socalled">description</quote> of actual usage after
that initial state can be more simply created, maintained, and studied. 
</para>


<para>Lojban is undoubtedly the most carefully designed and defined AL ever
created.  All aspects of its design have been carefully engineered by
several people encompassing expertise in a variety of disciplines,
including linguistics.  The language prescription is similarly the most
complete of any language.  As such, it serves as a unique basis for the
study of language usage and language change.  </para>


<para>A new language like Lojban, with no native speakers, is termed a
<quote role="socalled">pidgin</quote>.  As the language evolves, native speakers of other languages will
learn it, and will bring into their Lojban usage the perspective and
patterns of their native language.  This interaction process, called
<quote role="socalled">creolization</quote>, affects all languages, and may be the principle cause of
language change.  As Lojban is learned by speakers of a variety of natural
languages, this process can be studied directly in a way never before
possible, with the language prescription serving as a standard by which
deviations associated with speaker origin, and evolution of usage, can be
measured and described in detail.  </para>


<para>An AL like Lojban has neither an associated <quote role="socalled">native accent</quote> nor a
culture base.  Being much simpler and more regular than a natural language,
an adult speaker should acquire a fluency seldom achieved when studying a
natural language, and in a relatively short time.  Lojban thus makes
possible relatively short-term studies of language learning and language
change.  Processes that take generations in natural languages may be
observed in a few years in Lojban speakers.  </para>


<para>With the learning of other languages acquiring critical importance in
today's international economy, Lojban provides a tool for researching in
language acquisition.  Again, Lojban's simplicity allows the results of
such research to be obtained more quickly than in similar studies of
natural language acquisition.  </para>


<para>No claim is made that studying Lojban will tell <quote role="socalled">all</quote> about language. 
While Lojban has already seen considerable communicative use, as far as the
rigorous standards of linguistics are concerned it will only be a <quote role="socalled">model</quote>
of a language at least for several decades, whose <quote role="socalled">naturalness</quote> will be
suspect.  However, to the extent that Lojban serves the communicative and
expressive functions of human language, any theory about the nature of
human language must apply to Lojban.  Language features and processes
identified in studying Lojban can then be confirmed in natural languages. 
Similarly, theories of the nature of language can be tested and refined
against this simpler model of a language before facing the more difficult
and time-consuming testing and analysis involved in natural language
research.  </para>


<para>Because Lojban is relatively culture-free, and because of its
prescribed structure that is consistent with predicate logic, Lojban is an
ideal medium for the analysis and description of other languages. 
Currently, features in language must be compared against other natural
languages, and are usually described in scientific literature by glossed
translation into English.  Lojban is simple and regular enough to be
acquired as a metalanguage for describing other languages; its structures
allow clearer reflection of the patterns of the language being described,
without interference from the competing patterns of English.  </para>


<para>It is believed that, for anyone planning to later learn other
languages, the short time spent learning Lojban will be made up by the
reduced time needed later to learn those others.  Studies in the 1930s, for
example, demonstrated that students could acquire greater skill in French
through one semester of Esperanto followed by one semester of French, than
they could by a full year course in French.  Lojban offers similar
benefits, less likely to be limited to European languages.  For example,
structures in Japanese that are difficult to explain in English because
they are so unlike English usage are much easier to explain using Lojban
patterns.  Such study can be tied in with concepts of logic, and possibly
with computer-related activities, helping to show the essential
interrelated nature of language and other human endeavor.  </para>


<para>Finally, Lojban's predicate grammar, makes it eminently suited for
ongoing computer research into natural languages.  Lojban can be used for
parsing and analysis, as an internal medium of data storage, or as an
intermediate language for machine translation.  Having a combination of
logical and natural language structures, Lojban combines the best of both
major structural approaches to language processing in computers.  </para>


<para>The exercise of trying to invent a language can teach us things about
language that probably can't be learned in any other way.  Even if Lojban
should fail as a language, we will learn.  However, to the extent Lojban
succeeds, its potential as a basis for testing ideas about language, its
structure, and usage, is unlimited.  The invention of Lojban is the
invention of the science of experimental linguistics.  </para>

<para>
<literallayout>
Event contours, Aristoteleian Events





Insert
reply.doc (Cowan to Zwicky)

Insert lojling.doc
</literallayout>
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>