<part id="sect1"><title>What is Lojban? &mdash; <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la lojban mo</foreignphrase></title><titleabbrev>What is Lojban?</titleabbrev>

<chapter id="lojbanmo"><title>What is Lojban? &mdash; <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la lojban mo</foreignphrase></title><titleabbrev>What is Lojban?</titleabbrev>
<qandaset>

<qandaentry>

<question><para>What is Lojban?</para></question>

<answer> <para>Lojban
(/LOZH-bahn/) is a constructed
language. Originally called <quote role="socalled">Loglan</quote><indexterm id="idx2">
<primary>Loglan</primary></indexterm> by
project founder Dr. James Cooke Brown,<indexterm id="idx3">
<primary>Brown, James Cooke</primary>
</indexterm> who started the language development
in 1955, the goals for the language were first described in the article
<citetitle>Loglan</citetitle> in <citetitle>Scientific
American</citetitle>, June 1960. Made well-known by that article and by
occasional references in science fiction and computer publications,
Loglan/Lojban has been built over four decades by dozens of workers and
hundreds of supporters, led since 1987 by <link linkend="llg">The Logical Language
Group.</link><indexterm id="idx4">
<primary>Logical Language Group</primary>
</indexterm></para>


<para>There are many artificial languages, but Loglan/Lojban has been
<emphasis>engineered</emphasis> to make it unique in several ways. The
following are the main features of Lojban:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>Lojban is designed to be used by people in communication
with each other, and possibly in the future with
computers.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Lojban is designed to be culturally
neutral.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Lojban grammar is based on the principles of
logic.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Lojban has an unambiguous grammar.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Lojban has phonetic spelling, and sounds can be divided into
words in only one way.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Lojban is simple compared to natural languages; it is easy
to learn.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Lojban's 1350 root words can be easily combined to form a
vocabulary of millions of words.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Lojban is regular; the rules of the language don't have
exceptions.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Lojban attempts to remove restrictions on creative and
clear thought and communication.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Lojban has a variety of uses, ranging from creative to
scientific, from theoretical to practical.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>



<para>The following sections examine each of these points, while answering
the questions most often asked about Lojban.</para>

</answer>

</qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>Why was Lojban developed?</para> </question>

<answer> <para>Lojban was originally designed for the purpose of supporting
research on a concept known as the Sapir&ndash;Whorf hypothesis<indexterm id="idx5">
<primary>Sapir&ndash;Whorf hypothesis</primary>
</indexterm>. Simply
expressed, this hypothesis states that the structure of a language
constrains the thinking of people using that language. Lojban allows the
full expressive capability of a natural language, but differs in structure
from other languages in major ways. This allows its use as a test vehicle<indexterm id="idx6">
<primary>linguistic testing</primary>
</indexterm>
for scientists studying the relationships between language, thought, and
culture. If you are reading this as part of the introductory booklet, further discussion of these issues can be found in the chapter <xref
linkend="sect2" endterm="sect2title"/>.</para>

</answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>Are there other uses for Lojban?</para>
</question>

<answer> <para>Yes, several. Due to its unambiguous grammar and simple
structure, it also can be easily parsed<indexterm id="id7">
<primary>parsing</primary>
</indexterm> (broken down for analysis) by
computers<indexterm id="idx44">
<primary>computer applications</primary>
</indexterm>, making it possible for Lojban to be used in the future for
computer&ndash;human interaction<indexterm id="idx8">
<primary>computer&ndash;human interaction</primary>
</indexterm>, and perhaps conversation. Lojban's
structure is similar to existing artificial intelligence (AI)<indexterm id="idx9">
<primary>artificial intelligence (AI)</primary>
</indexterm> programming
languages, and will likely be a most powerful adjunct to AI research,
especially in the storing and processing of data about the world and
people's conceptions of it. There are also linguists interested in Lojban's
potential as an intermediate language in computer-aided translation<indexterm id="idx10">
<primary>computer-aided translation</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm id="idx11">
<primary>translation, computer-aided</primary>
<see>computer-aided translation</see>
</indexterm><indexterm id="idx45">
<primary>computer applications</primary>
</indexterm> of
natural languages; and Lojban is of interest as a potential stepping-stone
for students learning other languages. Because Lojban was designed to be
culturally neutral<indexterm id="idx12">
<primary>cultural neutrality</primary>
</indexterm>, and has a powerful vocabulary easily learned by people
of different language origins, some are interested in Lojban's potential as
an international language<indexterm id="idx13">
<primary>international language</primary>
</indexterm>. These are only the beginnings of the Lojban
applications that will be developed in the future.</para>

</answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>Is Lojban a computer language?</para>
</question>

<answer> <para>Lojban was designed as a <emphasis>human
language</emphasis>, and not as a computer language. It is therefore
intended for use in conversation, reading, writing, and thinking. However,
since Lojban can be processed by a computer much more easily than can a
natural language, it is only a matter of time before Lojban-based computer
applications<indexterm id="idx46">
<primary>computer applications</primary>
</indexterm> are developed. Learning and using Lojban doesn't require you
to know anything about computers or to talk like one.</para> </answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>How is Lojban written? How does it
sound?</para> </question>

<answer><para>Lojban uses letters of the Roman alphabet to represent its 6
vowels and 17 consonants<indexterm id="idx14">
<primary>orthography</primary>
</indexterm>; the Lojban character set uses only standard
typewriter or computer keyboard keys; capitalization<indexterm id="idx15">
<primary>capitalization</primary>
</indexterm> is rarely used to
indicate unusual stress in the pronunciation of names. Punctuation<indexterm id="idx16">
<primary>punctuation</primary>
</indexterm> is
spoken as words. The written language corresponds exactly to the sounds of
the spoken language; spelling is phonetic and unambiguous, and the flowing
sounds of the language break down into words in only one possible way. These features make
computer speech recognition and transcription more practical. Learning to
pronounce and spell Lojban is trivial.</para>


<para>Lojban has a smooth, rhythmic sound, somewhat like Italian. However,
its consonants create a fullness and power found in Slavic languages like
Russian, and the large number of vowel pairs impart a hint of Chinese,
Polynesian, and other Oriental languages, though without the tones that make
many of those languages difficult for others to learn.</para>


<para>Because there are no idioms to shorten expressions, a Lojban text is often
longer than the corresponding colloquial English text. The
unambiguous linguistic structures that result are a major benefit that makes this
worthwhile.</para>


<para>As an example of Lojban, Occam's Razor (<quote>The simplest
explanation is usually the best</quote>) may be translated:

<informalexample><literallayout><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">roda poi velcki cu so'eroi ganai saprai gi xagrai</foreignphrase>
/roh-dah poi VEHL-shkee shoo soh-heh-ROI GAH-nai SAHP-rai, ghee KHAH-grai/
<wordasword>All somethings which-are explanations mostly-are (if superlatively-simple then superlatively-good).</wordasword></literallayout></informalexample>
The apostrophe is pronounced like a short, breathy <quote
role="gloss">h</quote>, and is used to clearly separate the two adjacent
vowels for a listener, without requiring a pause between them.</para>
</answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>What kind of grammar does Lojban have?</para>
</question>

<answer> <para><quote role="gloss">Grammar</quote> is a word with painful
memories for many of us. But though Lojban grammar seems strange at first
sight, it is actually quite simple. It is based on a system called
predicate logic, which states that in any sentence you have a
<firstterm>relationship</firstterm><indexterm id="idx17">
<primary><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">selbri</emphasis></foreignphrase></primary>
</indexterm><indexterm id="idx18"><primary>relationship</primary>
<see><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">selbri</emphasis></foreignphrase></see>
</indexterm><indexterm id="idx19"><primary>predicate</primary>
<see><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">selbri</emphasis></foreignphrase></see>
</indexterm> (<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">selbri</emphasis></foreignphrase> in Lojban) between one or more
<firstterm>arguments</firstterm> (<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">sumti</emphasis></foreignphrase>)<indexterm id="idx20">
<primary><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">sumti</emphasis></foreignphrase></primary>
</indexterm><indexterm id="idx21"><primary>argument</primary>
<see><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">selbri</emphasis></foreignphrase></see>
</indexterm>. An argument can be a thing,
event, quality or just about anything (quite how you can have a
relationship of one argument is one of the mysteries of predicate logic!).
To give an example, the English sentence

<informalexample><literallayout>Chris adores Pat </literallayout>
</informalexample>has a relation <wordasword>adore</wordasword>, between two arguments,
<wordasword>Chris</wordasword> and <wordasword>Pat</wordasword>. In Lojban
this would be

<informalexample><literallayout><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">la kris. prami la pat.</foreignphrase></literallayout>

</informalexample>or, if you prefer,

<informalexample><literallayout><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">la kris. la pat. prami</foreignphrase></literallayout>

</informalexample>(The full stops mean that you have to pause slightly to separate the
words &mdash;
anythingelseinLojbancanberuntogetherwithoutbeingmisunderstood). </para>


<para>You might be thinking <quote>Well in that case a function is a verb
and an argument is a noun, so why bother with special terminology like
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">selbri</emphasis></foreignphrase> and
whatnot?</quote> However, in Lojban Chris's feelings about Pat might be
described like this:

<informalexample> <literallayout><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">la pat. melbi</foreignphrase>
Pat is beautiful.</literallayout> </informalexample></para>

<para>In English you have a verb (<quote role="gloss">doing word</quote>),
<wordasword>is</wordasword>, and an adjective (<quote
role="gloss">describing word</quote>), <wordasword>beautiful</wordasword>.
In Turkish, you would say <wordasword>Pat g&uuml;zel</wordasword>, which is
a noun and an adjective, with no verb required. In Chinese you would use
<wordasword>meili</wordasword>, a <quote role="gloss">stative verb</quote>
&mdash; but enough! In Lojban you don't need all this. </para>


<para>Now, if there are no nouns, verbs, subjects or objects in Lojban, how
do we know that <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">la kris. la pat.
prami</foreignphrase> means that Chris adores Pat and not the other way?
Different languages handle this problem differently. In English it is done
with word order, and when that isn't enough, with prepositions (words like
<wordasword>at</wordasword>, <wordasword>from</wordasword>,
<wordasword>to</wordasword>, <wordasword>with</wordasword> and so on). In
other languages, like Latin or Turkish, it's done by changing the form of
the words, e.g. <wordasword>Pat'i Chris sever</wordasword> in Turkish means
<quote>Chris loves Pat</quote>, not <quote>Pat loves Chris.</quote> </para>

<para>In Lojban, the order in which arguments appear is built in to the meaning of the word. For example,
the word <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">dunda</foreignphrase> means
<wordasword>give</wordasword>, but its full meaning is:

<informalexample><literallayout>x<subscript>1</subscript> gives x<subscript>2</subscript> to x<subscript>3</subscript></literallayout></informalexample></para>


<para>So <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">mi pu dunda le cuska le
ninmu</foreignphrase> means <quote>I gave the book to the woman</quote>,
not <quote>I gave the woman to the book</quote>). </para>


<para>The important point is that Lojban has a lot of what we would call
<quote role="gloss">grammar</quote>, but nearly all of this is contained in
the <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">cmavo</emphasis></foreignphrase><indexterm id="idx22">
<primary><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">cmavo</emphasis></foreignphrase></primary>
</indexterm><indexterm id="idx23"><primary>structure word</primary>
<see><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">sumti</emphasis></foreignphrase></see>
</indexterm> (structure
words), and you can use as many or as few of them as you want. </para>

</answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>What else is distinctive about Lojban
grammar?</para> </question>

<answer> <para>In Lojban, it is equally easy to speak of something as being an
action as it is for it being a state of existence. The distinction between the
two can be ignored, or can be explicitly expressed by associating concepts
in <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> metaphors<indexterm id="idx24">
<primary><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase></primary>
</indexterm><indexterm id="idx25"><primary>metaphor</primary>
<see><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase></see>
</indexterm>
(combinations of <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">selbri</emphasis></foreignphrase>)
involving words like <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">gasnu</foreignphrase>
(<quote role="gloss">do</quote>), <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">zasti</foreignphrase> (<quote
role="gloss">exist</quote>), <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">zukte</foreignphrase> (<quote role="gloss">act with
purpose</quote>); with a variety of <quote role="gloss">operators</quote>
(<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">cmavo</emphasis></foreignphrase>) dealing with
abstractions<indexterm id="idx26">
<primary>abstraction</primary>
</indexterm> such as events, states, properties, amounts, ideas,
experience, and truth; or with four pre-defined varieties of causality<indexterm id="idx27">
<primary>causality</primary>
</indexterm>
(others can be developed through metaphor).</para>



<para>A major benefit of using a predicate grammar is that Lojban doesn't
have inflections and declensions on nouns, verbs, and adjectives.
Most natural languages have evolved such variations to reduce ambiguity as
to how words are related in a sentence. Language change has made
these inflections and declensions highly irregular and thus difficult to
learn. Lojban uses the simple but flexible predicate relationship to erase
both the irregularity and the declensions.</para>


<para>Tense and location markers (inflections), adverbs, and prepositions
are combined into one part of speech.<indexterm id="idx28">
<primary><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">cmavo</emphasis></foreignphrase></primary>
</indexterm><indexterm id="idx29">
<primary>tense</primary>
</indexterm> New preposition-like forms can be
built at will from predicates; these allow the user to expand upon a
sentence by attaching and relating arguments not normally included in the
meaning of a word.</para>


<para>Numbers and quantifiers<indexterm id="idx30">
<primary>quantifiers</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm id="idx31">
<primary>numbers</primary><see>quantifiers</see>
</indexterm> are conceptually expanded from natural
languages. <wordasword>Many</wordasword>, <wordasword>enough</wordasword>,
<wordasword>too much</wordasword>, <wordasword>a few</wordasword>, and
<wordasword>at least</wordasword> are among concepts that are expressed as
numbers in Lojban. Thus <quote>it costs $3.95</quote> and <quote>it costs
too much</quote> are grammatically identical, and one can talk of being
<quote>enough-th in line</quote> for tickets to a sellout movie. Core
concepts of logic, mathematics, and science are built into the root
vocabulary. They enhance discussion of those topics, and are surprisingly
useful in ordinary speech, too.</para>


<para>Predicate logic can express a wide variety of human thought; Lojban
also has non-logical constructs that do not affect or obscure the logical
structure, allowing communications that are not amenable to logical
analysis. For example, Lojban has a full set of emotional indicators<indexterm id="idx31a">
<primary>attitudinals</primary>
</indexterm>, are similar to such
ejaculations in English as <wordasword>Oh!</wordasword>,
<wordasword>Aha!</wordasword>, and <wordasword>Wheee!</wordasword>, but
each has a specific meaning. Similarly, Lojban has indicators of the
speaker's relationship to what is said (is it hearsay, direct observation,
logical deduction, etc.?) similar to those found in some American Indian
languages.</para>


<para>Lojban supports metalinguistic discussion<indexterm id="idx32">
<primary>metalinguistic language</primary>
</indexterm> about the sentences being
spoken while remaining unambiguous. <!--(<quote>This sentence is not
true</quote> need not be a paradox in Lojban.) -->Lojban also supports a
variety of <quote role="gloss">tense</quote> logic that allows one to be extremely
specific about time and space (and space&ndash;time) relationships, even
those implied by the concept of time travel. A substantial portion of
Lojban's grammar is designed to support unambiguous statement of
mathematical expressions<indexterm id="idx33">
<primary>mathematical expressions</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm id="idx34">
<primary>MEX</primary><see>mathematical expressions</see>
</indexterm> and relations in a manner compatible both with
international usage and the rest of Lojban's grammar.</para>


<para>Lojban <quote role="gloss">parts of speech</quote> are convertible
from one to another by using short structure words (called <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">cmavo</emphasis></foreignphrase>)<indexterm id="idx35">
<primary><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">cmavo</emphasis></foreignphrase></primary>
</indexterm>. One can make numbers serve as
nouns or verbs, or can invent new numbers and prepositions. Lojban removes
many of the constraints on human thought, while preserving tight control on
structural syntax.</para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>Lojban seems complex. How hard is it to
learn?</para> </question>

<answer> <para>Lojban is actually much simpler than natural languages. It
is only slightly more complex in its grammar than the current generation of computer
languages (such as Ada and Perl). Lojban seems complex only because the
varieties of human thought are complex, and Lojban is designed to minimize
constraints on those thoughts. Lojban text appears longer and more complex
due to its lack of idiom, its complete explicitness of logical structure, and
most importantly, its unfamiliarity. On the other hand, conversational
speech uses less than half of the possible grammatical structures, leaving
the rest for writing and for other circumstances when one is likely to take
time to carefully formulate exact logical phrasings.</para>


<para>Lojban's pronunciation, spelling, word formation, and grammar rules
are fixed, and the language is free of exceptions to these rules. Such
exceptions are the bane of learning to speak natural language <emphasis>correctly</emphasis>.
Without the burden of ambiguity, Lojban users
can be precise and specific more easily than in other languages.</para>


<para>Because Lojban's grammar is simple, it is easier to learn than other
languages. A working vocabulary including the complete set of 1350 root
words takes about 8&ndash;12 weeks of study at 1 hour per day. It is by no
means uncommon for people who embark on learning Lojban to be able to write
grammatical Lojban within a few days, and to hold at least a limited
conversation within a few weeks. Natural languages, especially English,
take several years to learn to a comparable level
of skill.</para>


<para>The available Lojban teaching materials are so structured that you
can learn the language without classroom instruction or
a close community of speakers. Communication practice with others is needed
to achieve fluency, but you can start using the language as you achieve
proficiency.</para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>What do you mean by <quote
role="socalled">unambiguous</quote>?</para> </question>

<answer> <para><indexterm id="idx36" class="startofrange">
<primary>unambiguous language</primary>
</indexterm>Lojban has an unambiguous grammar (proven by computer
analysis of a formal grammar<indexterm id="idx47">
<primary>grammar, formal</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm id="idx48">
<primary>formal grammar</primary><see>grammar, formal</see>
</indexterm><indexterm id="idx49">
<primary>machine grammar</primary><see>grammar, formal</see>
</indexterm>), pronunciation<indexterm id="idx50">
<primary>phonology</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm id="idx51">
<primary>pronunciation</primary><see>phonology</see>
</indexterm>, and <firstterm>morphology</firstterm><indexterm id="idx52">
<primary>morphology</primary>
</indexterm> (word forms).
In practice this means that the person who reads or hears a Lojban sentence
is never in doubt as to what words it contains or what roles they play in
the sentence. This is true even if the words are unfamiliar, so long as the
spelling and grammar rules are known. Lojban has no words that sound alike
but have different meanings (like <wordasword>herd</wordasword> and
<wordasword>heard</wordasword>), that have multiple unrelated meanings
(<wordasword>set</wordasword>), or that differ only in punctuation but
not in sound (like the abominable <wordasword>its</wordasword> and
<wordasword>it's</wordasword>). There is never any doubt about where
words begin and end (if you hear <wordasword>cargo
ship</wordasword>, do you hear two words or three?) Most important, the
function of each word is inescapably clear; there is nothing like the
English sentence <wordasword>Time flies like an arrow</wordasword>, in which any of
the first three words could be the verb.</para>


<para>Lojban is <emphasis>not</emphasis> entirely unambiguous, of course;
human beings occasionally desire to be ambiguous in their expressions. In
Lojban, this ambiguity is limited to semantics, metaphor, and intentional
omission of information (ellipsis).</para>


<para>Semantic ambiguity results because words in natural languages
represent families of concepts rather than individual meanings. These
meanings often have only weak semantic relationships to each other (the
English word <wordasword>run</wordasword> is an outstanding example<!--; and
auxiliary verbs are almost impossible to describe as having a meaning on
their own-->.) In addition, each individual's personal experiences provide
emotional connotations to words. By providing a fresh, culturally-neutral
start, Lojban attempts to minimize the transference of these associations
as people learn the language. Most Lojban words do not much resemble
corresponding words in other languages; the differences aid in making this
fresh start possible.</para>


<para>Lojban's powerful metaphor and word-building features make it easy to
make fine distinctions between concepts. This discourages the tendency for
individual words to acquire families of meanings. Lojban metaphors (called
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase><indexterm id="idx38">
<primary><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase></primary>
</indexterm>) are themselves
ambiguous; they specify a relationship between concepts, but not what the
relationship is. That relationship can be made explicit using unambiguous
logical constructs if necessary, or can be left as vague as the speaker
(usually) desires. Similarly, portions of the logical structure of a Lojban
expression can be omitted, greatly simplifying the expression while causing
some ambiguity. Unlike in the natural languages, though, this ambiguity is
readily identified by a reader or listener. Thus all ambiguity in Lojban is
constrained and recognizable, and can be clarified as necessary by further
interaction.</para>


<para>This precision in no way confines the meaning of a Lojban sentence.
It is possible to be fanciful or ridiculous, to tell a lie, or to be
misunderstood. You can be very specific, or you can be intentionally vague.
Your hearer may not understand what you <emphasis>meant</emphasis>, but
will always understand what you <emphasis>said</emphasis>.<indexterm id="idx37" class="endofrange" startref="idx36">
<primary>unambiguous language</primary>
</indexterm></para>

</answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>Can you make jokes in an unambiguous
language?</para> </question>

<answer> <para><indexterm id="idx39">
<primary>humor</primary>
</indexterm>Most humor arises from situation and character and is as
funny in Lojban as in any language. Humor based on word play, of course, is
language-dependent. Lojban has no homonyms, and hence no simple puns; puns
derived from similar sounds are still possible, and have in fact been
attempted (for example in the Lojban translation of <citetitle>Alice in
Wonderland</citetitle><indexterm id="idx40">
<primary><citetitle>Alice in
Wonderland</citetitle></primary>
</indexterm>). Since Lojban will almost always be a second
language, bilingual puns and word play abound, often based on the relative
ambiguity of the other languages involved. Humor based on internal
grammatical ambiguity is of course impossible in Lojban, but humor based on
nonsensical statements, or on logical structures that would be difficult to
clearly express in another language, becomes easier.</para>


<para>As speakers become fluent, and conventional phrases come into use,
Lojban will develop its own forms of spoonerisms and subtle puns. Unique
forms of Lojban word-play have already turned up; they exploit the way
small variations in Lojban grammar create unexpected variations in meaning,
and the capability to simply express rather mind-boggling relationships.
Like all word-play, these lose zest when translated into other
languages.</para>


<para>Related to humor is the aphorism: the pithy saying that gains
pungency or poignancy from terse, elegant phrasing. Lojban seems as capable
of aphorisms as any language, perhaps more than most; however, because the
language is so young, few such aphorisms have been devised to date.</para> </answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question>

<para>Isn't Esperanto the <quote role="gloss">international
language</quote>?</para> </question> <answer>

<para><indexterm id="idx41" class="startofrange">
<primary>international language</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm id="idx43">
<primary>Esperanto</primary>
</indexterm>There have been hundreds of artificial international languages
developed, of which Esperanto is the most successful and widely known.
Esperanto, like most other such languages, was based on European languages
in both grammar and vocabulary. Although it manages to be relatively neutral
between them, it still retains an inherent cultural bias which makes it
unsuited for most of the purposes that Lojban was designed for.</para>


<para>Lojban is culturally fully neutral. Its vocabulary was built
algorithmically using today's six most widely spoken languages: Chinese,
Hindi, English, Russian, Spanish, and Arabic. Lojban's words thus show
roots in three major families of languages spoken by most of the world's
people. Lojban's grammar accommodates structures found in non-European
languages, and uses sounds found in many of the world's languages. Coupled
with the potential computer applications<indexterm id="idx53">
<primary>computer applications</primary>
</indexterm> that will make Lojban a useful
language to know, Lojban's potential as an
international language may be more far-reaching than Esperanto's.</para>


<para>Lojban was not designed primarily to be an international language,
however, but rather as a linguistic tool for studying and understanding language.
Its linguistic and computer applications make Lojban unique among proposed
international languages: Lojban can be successful without
immediately being accepted and adopted everywhere, and Lojban can be useful
and interesting even to those skeptical of or hostile towards the
international language movement.</para>


<para>Since Lojban is also not in direct competition with Esperanto,
it has proven attractive to Esperantists
interested in acquiring a new perspective on their own international
language, who feel less threatened because Lojban has different goals.

Lojban's supporters recognize that it will take decades for Lojban to
acquire both the number and variety of speakers and the extensive history
of usage that marks Esperanto culture. Meanwhile, each language community
has much to learn from each other; this process has started and is
well underway.</para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question>

<para>How about English as an international language?</para> </question>
<answer>

<para>English is commonly used as an <quote role="gloss">international
language</quote> in the fields of science and technology, and is probably
the most widely spoken language in the world. American dominance of
technology in the twentieth century has caused massive borrowing from English into
other languages that do not have words for all these new concepts. This
dominance, and a heritage of colonialism and imperialism that has built
resentment towards American and European impositions on native culture, has
caused recent movements in other countries <emphasis>away</emphasis> from
English. The rising influence of other non&ndash;English-speaking countries on world
economics, science, and technology makes further declines in the
universality of English likely.</para>


<para>In addition, most who know English as a second language speak it only
minimally, though they may be able to read or understand many words. India
is a prominent example of a country where English is the only language more
or less understood throughout the country, which has about 1500 languages
and dialects; but the English spoken in India is often unintelligible by
Americans or Britons. In fact, English is one of the most
difficult languages to learn to use well. In countries where English is spoken
along with other languages, it has been adapted into dialects which match
the local culture and borrow words from the other local languages. Some of
these dialects are as much as 70% unintelligible to American or British
speakers, or to each other. As such, there is no single English language to
call an <quote role="gloss">international</quote> one.</para>


<para>Lojban is a single language, with design features to discourage
breaking up into separate languages. While it was developed primarily by Americans, and
was designed to be at least as expressive as English is, Lojban's cultural neutrality gives
equal priority to the structures and concepts of other languages and
cultures. This cultural neutrality enhances Lojban's acceptability as an
international language. Since it is as capable as English is of generating or borrowing
any words needed to support the concepts of science and technology, 
and has its special advantages for computer applications<indexterm id="idx43a">
<primary>computer applications</primary>
</indexterm>, Lojban is likely to
spread worldwide through the technological community. Far more so than
English, Lojban is simple and easy to learn for people of all
cultures.<indexterm id="idx42" class="endofrange" startref="idx41">
<primary>international language</primary>
</indexterm></para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question>

<para>Can poetry be written in a <quote role="socalled">logical</quote>
language or an <quote role="socalled">unambiguous</quote> one?</para>
</question> <answer>

<para>Original poetry<indexterm id="idx55a">
<primary>poetry</primary>
</indexterm> has already been written in Lojban, and some has been
translated into the language. Lojban's powerful metaphor structure<indexterm id="idx56">
<primary><foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase></primary>
</indexterm> allows
you to build concepts into words easily, as you need them. A Lojban speaker
doesn't need a dictionary to use and understand millions of words that can
potentially exist in the language. The absence of cultural constraints
makes consideration of new ideas and relationships easier than in natural
languages, spurring creativity. Lojban aids in communicating abstractions
by identifying their nature explicitly. Lojban is a thus a very powerful
language, not only for poetry, but for discussing such abstract fields as
philosophy, physics, metaphysics, and religion.</para>


<para>Lojban poets are already experimenting with new (and old) forms of
poetry that seem especially well suited to the rhythm, sound, and flow of
the language. Not since the Middle Ages have poets had such an opportunity
to affect the development of a new language, as they now can with Lojban.
Lojban's rich and powerful <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> have been used to create colorful
images and to convey moving emotions. Unhindered by grammatical ambiguity
that can obscure desired meanings, Lojban unleashes the full potential of
poetic expression to communicate both concrete and abstract ideas.</para>
</answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>How was Lojban developed?</para> </question>
<answer>

<para>The language, then called <quote role="gloss">Loglan</quote><indexterm id="idx57">
<primary>Loglan</primary>
</indexterm>, was
first described in the 1950s, by Dr. James Cooke Brown<indexterm id="idx57a">
<primary>Brown, James Cooke</primary>
</indexterm>. The 1960 Scientific
American article <citetitle>Loglan</citetitle> was his call for assistance
in developing the language. A revolution in linguistics was simultaneously
taking place, resulting in a rapidly increasing knowledge of the nature of
human language; this changed the requirements for the developing language.
The first widely distributed Loglan dictionary and language description did
not appear until 1975; the incompleteness of this description and continued
development work discouraged people from learning the language.
Furthermore, computers caught up with Loglan just then, making it possible
to refine the grammar, eliminate ambiguity and mathematically prove its
absence. For over forty years, this work has been performed by volunteers, and
without financial support. Now, after several versions of the language,
people have been learning and using the current version, which is the first to be
called <quote role="gloss">Lojban</quote> (from the roots
<quote>logical-language</quote> in Lojban).</para>


<para>This version is the first version with a stable vocabulary, and the
first to have a stable and completely defined grammar. The stabilization of
the language in this version has followed a painstaking and extensive
period of research and analysis, between 1988 and 1998. Thus, in an
important sense, Lojban is a very new language. To ensure Lojban remains
stable while people learn it, the language definition is being closely
controlled; the grammar and vocabulary has already been baselined<indexterm id="idx58">
<primary>baseline</primary>
</indexterm> (frozen)
for several years. When the number of speakers has grown significantly, and
a Lojban literature has developed, Lojban will be treated like a natural
language and allowed to grow and flourish without constraint, as do other
natural languages.</para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>How many people speak Lojban?</para>
</question> <answer>

<para><indexterm id="idx59">
<primary>Lojban</primary><secondary>number of speakers of</secondary>
</indexterm>Questions of how many people speak a language greatly depend on your
presuppositions and definitions &mdash; which a language like Lojban, at
least, can make explicit! The on-line Lojban mailing list<indexterm id="idx60">
<primary>Lojban mailing list</primary>
</indexterm>, which
constitutes the largest community of people using the language, has over
200 subscribers, with well over 20 regular posters as of this writing. The
level of confidence of the language community has already risen to such a
level that there is a Lojban-language&ndash;only discussion group, as well as
the general mailing list. Lojban has also been used extensively in
real-time conversation, both electronically (IRC) and face-to-face. Though
the Lojban-speaking community is so widely diffused that the opportunity
for conversation does not arise frequently, the number of Lojbanists who
can sustain a conversation in the language certainly ranges beyond what can
be counted on the fingers of one hand, and is steadily increasing. Lojban
has been proven in communicative use for well over a decade, and the range
and expressivity of the language is being continually explored by the
language community.</para>


<para>The first speakers of Lojban have a unique opportunity. They are the
history-makers who will shape the flavor of the first totally new language
to achieve broad speakability. Their ideas will be most influential in
setting the patterns of usage that others will learn from. Their
experiences will teach things about language that have never before been
learned &mdash; or learnable.</para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>Why should I learn Lojban?</para> </question>
<answer>

<para>There are several reasons for learning the language now. Those who
are working with the language now are actively consulted for their opinions
on how to teach and spread the language. Within a few weeks of work
learning from the materials already written, you will
be able to work with those who have already started. You will be a
significant part of this small but rapidly growing community. You will
receive personal attention to any problems you have with the language
from those leading the effort. If you are truly ambitious and committed to
the language, you are welcome to join in that leadership.</para>


<para>Those with a computer background who learn the language now will be
the leaders in developing the earliest practical computer applications<indexterm id="idx54">
<primary>computer applications</primary>
</indexterm> for
the language. Expertise in the language will no doubt be valuable if Lojban
becomes recognized as a useful tool for computer applications by the
computer industry. Meanwhile, computer-oriented Lojbanists can also aid in
developing computer-aided instruction tools or converting existing software
to run on new computers.</para>


<para>People not interested in computers will also find Lojban a valuable
language. You may be interested in the Sapir&ndash;Whorf hypothesis<indexterm id="idx61">
<primary>Sapir&ndash;Whorf hypothesis</primary>
</indexterm>, and in
the scientific tests to be planned and conducted, or in other
language-related research. You may be interested in Lojban's potential as
an international language, and in the attempts to use the language to reach
across cultural boundaries.</para>


<para>Regardless of your background, you will find learning Lojban to be a
mind-expanding experience. Learning any language other than your native
tongue broadens your perspectives and allows you to transcend the necessarily limited
viewpoints of your native language culture. Lojban, being much simpler to
learn than natural languages, provides this benefit much more quickly than
does the study of other languages. And being quite different to natural languages,
Lojban provides this benefit more directly.</para>


<para>Having learned Lojban, you will find it easier to learn other
languages and to communicate with people from other backgrounds, regardless
of the language studied; the linguistic principles you learn while learning
Lojban are applicable to these languages and the communication problems they entail. The
logical organization embedded in Lojban will aid you in organizing and
clarifying your thoughts. Your new perspective on language,
ambiguity, and communication will allow you to express those thoughts more
clearly, even when you use an ambiguous natural language.</para>


<para>You needn't learn Lojban for any practical purpose, however. Many, if
not most, of those who are learning Lojban are doing so because it is fun.
Learning Lojban is intellectually stimulating, providing human interaction
(a way to meet other people and get to know them) and mental challenge.
Lojban has all the benefits of games designed for entertainment, with the
side benefit of that entertainment developing into a useful skill.</para>


<para>Learning Lojban as an intellectual toy
means that you can get enjoyment from learning Lojban without anywhere near
the effort needed to benefit from studying other languages. While becoming
fluent in Lojban will probably take hundreds of hours over several months,
you can feel some sense of accomplishment in the language after just a
couple of hours of study. You can use Lojban immediately for fun, while
gaining skill with greater experience.</para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>How do I learn Lojban?</para> </question>
<answer>

<para>This booklet includes a description of the grammar of Lojban and some
introductory learning materials.  If you are reading this text in a
separately printed brochure, you may write to the Logical Language
Group<indexterm id="idx62">
<primary>Logical Language Group</primary>
</indexterm> at the address found at the end of this brochure, and we
will be happy to provide the complete booklet.  We request a
contribution of $5 to cover its cost.</para>


<para>If you are reading this brochure on-line, or have access to the
Internet, the complete booklet is also available on the World Wide
Web for free at the address:

<informalexample>
<literallayout><computeroutput>&level0addr;</computeroutput></literallayout></informalexample></para>

<para>Once you have read this booklet, there are several
directions you may proceed, depending on your goals for use of the language.</para>


<para>Most people learning the language will work for some time on their
own before working with others. We recommend, where possible, that you
identify at least one other person to study and interact with, either in
person or by mail. The Logical Language Group maintains lists of Lojban
students of various degrees of skill and activity levels. There are also
both a general and an in-Lojban discussion group available on the Internet.
Information will be found below.</para>


<para>Almost any use you wish to make of Lojban requires some degree of
mastery of the basic vocabulary. You can learn enough Lojban grammar to
support conversation in just a couple of hours, but you will need
vocabulary in order to use that grammar.</para>


<para>You can learn the Lojban vocabulary using computer software. The
Logical Language Group has computer-aided&ndash;teaching programs
distributed under the name <citetitle>LogFlash</citetitle><indexterm id="idx63">
<primary><citetitle>LogFlash</citetitle></primary>
</indexterm>, with an MS-DOS/Windows
version currently available. The software is based on flash-card teaching
techniques, which are extremely efficient in helping you learn the
vocabulary. Other computer software is available, including a parser and a
glosser.</para>


<para>You can learn the Lojban grammar in several ways, including by
studying the examples in our on-line text archives and mailing
lists, and by going through the formal grammar<indexterm id="idx65">
<primary>grammar, formal</primary>
</indexterm>
description. (The formal grammars are available in two
formats, <citetitle>YACC</citetitle> and simplified <citetitle>E-BNF</citetitle>.  If you don't understand
these formats, don't worry.)</para>


<para>An introduction to the grammar of Lojban will be found in <xref
linkend="sect2" endterm="sect2title"/>. There is also a set of introductory
lessons available; these cover the basics of the language, but at a more
leisurely pace. For more advanced study, you may wish to use the draft
lessons written in the late 1980s (22 lessons); these draft lessons will
eventually form the basis of a Lojban textbook. A complete grammatical
description of Lojban, <citetitle>The Complete Lojban Language</citetitle><indexterm id="idx66">
<primary><citetitle>The Complete Lojban Language</citetitle></primary>
</indexterm>
by John W. Cowan, was published by the Logical Language Group in 1997. This
is an authoritative reference, and can be used as an aid to learning the advanced
features of the language.</para>


<para>A formal Lojban dictionary is being
compiled, and will encompass the word lists already available from the
Logical Language Group as of this writing. Draft versions of the dictionary
are available on the Lojban web site (see contact details below).</para>


<para>Of course the only way to really learn a language is to
<emphasis>use</emphasis> it. The Logical Language Group will assist you in
finding other Lojban students of comparable skill level and interests,
either in your local area or reachable by post or electronic mail. The
on-line Lojban discussion groups regularly contains Lojban text, some with
detailed translations and some without translation, as well as discussions
of language points by various members of the Lojban community. Of course
the best way to use the language is to recruit friends and associates into
studying and using the language with you. Even if they are not interested
in the same language goals as you are, the <quote
role="socalled">hobbyist</quote> aspect of the language will provide
interesting and stimulating entertainment for all concerned.</para>
</answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry id="llg"> <question><para>What is The Logical Language Group?</para>
</question> <answer>

<para><indexterm id="idx67" class="startofrange" significance="preferred">
<primary>Logical Language Group</primary>
</indexterm>The Logical Language Group, Inc. is a non-profit organization, the
embodiment of the Loglan/Lojban community. We were founded to complete the
language development process, to develop and publish teaching materials, to
organize and teach the community, to promote applications of Lojban, and to
initiate and lead research efforts in linguistics, language education, and
other areas related to Lojban. Simply put, our purpose is to serve you in
all manner of things Lojbanic. The Logical Language Group is not affiliated
with The Loglan Institute, Inc., the organization founded by James Cooke
Brown.</para>


<para>The Logical Language Group is also called <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la lojbangirz.</foreignphrase> (<wordasword>/lah
lozh-BAHN-geerz./</wordasword>), its Lojban name. It was founded informally
in 1987, and incorporated in 1988. The U.S. Internal Revenue Service
approved our status as a non-profit educational/scientific charity in 1989,
making donations and grants to the organization deductible under U.S. tax
law.</para>


<para>Loglan/Lojban has been developed almost totally by volunteer labor
and small donations of money. Lojban attracts people who are willing to
devote a lot of time and effort to seeing their dreams become reality.
Thus, our only income has been money derived from sales of our
publications, and donations from interested supporters.</para>

<para>The Logical Language Group publishes and sells printed materials on Lojban. 
<!--We distribute materials to people and ask that they
contribute to cover the costs of those materials. -->All language definition
information is considered in the public domain, and most Logical Language
Group publications are distributed under a policy which allows
not-for-charge copying and redistribution. Computer versions of many of our
publications are available on-line at no charge. We ask people who receive
our materials by any of these means to let us know,
so that we may better serve you, and donate
liberally, so that we may continue to serve you.</para>


<!--<para>We ask that you keep a positive account balance of up to a year or
more of expected expenditures for orders, as indicated on our registration
and order forms. Such balance money serves as our day-to-day operating
funds. We will refund positive balance contributions within 6 weeks of your
request. If you move without notifying us and we therefore cannot contact
you, we will maintain your positive balance for a year before treating it
as a donation.</para>-->


<para>Most materials that we sell require either prior payment, an informal
commitment to pay on your part, or your statement that you cannot afford to
pay for materials (in which case our supplying these materials is at our
discretion). We attempt to flexibly support Lojbanists who have financial
constraints, and will accept reasonable offers of reduced or delayed
payments subject to our financial condition, coupled with your commitment
to actively maintain contact and involvement with the community.
Obviously, the level of your prior and current activity and any commitments
you make to learning the language or to volunteer work for <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">la lojbangirz.</foreignphrase> will be factored into our
decision.</para>

<para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">la lojbangirz.</foreignphrase> has a
special commitment to support Lojbanists outside the U.S., because so many of the
language goals are dependent on building an international community of
speakers, and because we recognize the difficulties caused by the
international currency market and the relative wealth of nations. We can
accept bank cheques in most currencies and international payment via Master
Card and Visa. We also encourage groups to form so that they can receive a single copy
of our materials, copying or passing them to others to keep the per-person
costs low. We expect a lower standard of contact and contribution
from overseas Lojbanists when deciding on whether to continue sending our
materials at reduced or no charge.</para>


<!--<para>We ask that all recipients of our materials voluntarily contribute
what you can, and to maintain sufficient funds in your balance to cover our
suggested prices. These will be deducted automatically when we send you
materials. We will notify you requesting more money when your balance
becomes negative. We reserve the right to refuse orders when your balance
is not fully paid, but again will make every effort to support those who
support Lojban through their time, commitment, and money.</para>-->

<!--<para><emphasis role="bold">You have no legal obligation to pay for
materials sent to you without your request, but such materials will be
charged against your balance in the absence of any agreement
otherwise</emphasis>, with adjustments made to that balance per agreement.
If we accept an offer of reduced payment from you, we will charge that
amount to your balance.</para>-->

<para><emphasis role="bold">You have no legal obligation to pay for
materials sent to you without your request, but we reserve the right
to refuse to fill orders until any materials we have already sent you
are paid for (unless we agree to waive payment).</emphasis></para>

<para>We ask all recipients of our materials to help us financially in any
way you can. The Logical Language Group needs your gifts for support of the
Loglan/Lojban project. Artificial languages are historically not
self-sustaining financially, and have difficulty receiving outside support. The
Logical Language Group, Inc. is prohibited by its bylaws from spending more
than 15% of its expenses for administrative purposes, except by special
agreement with a donor who agrees to cover such added costs in full.</para>
</answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>How does The Logical Language Group serve the
community?</para> </question>

<answer> <para>The Logical Language Group coordinates and promotes
activities involving Lojban and the Lojban community. In that role, it
publishes materials enabling people to learn the language, and facilitates
their forming a community of speakers. Most people involved with Lojban
stay informed by checking our web page or participating in the Lojban
mailing lists (see contact details below). A printed newsletter
(<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le lojbo karni</foreignphrase>) and a
journal (<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ju'i lobypli</foreignphrase>)
<indexterm id="idx69">
<primary><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ju'i lobypli</foreignphrase></primary>
</indexterm>have been published intermittently, and may or may not be in active
publication when you read this. <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le lojbo
karni</foreignphrase> contains general news aimed at those not actively
involved in the learning and using the language. <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ju'i
lobypli</foreignphrase> contains discussions of features of the language,
debates on research issues and applications, letters from the community and
responses, and Lojban writings and translations.</para>


<para>Our printed publications are free of advertisements (other than our own
ordering information, and occasional mention of individuals and
organizations who have contributed particular service to our efforts); and
we do not sell our mailing list. Our publications are distributed as
cheaply as possible to encourage new people to participate. In the interest
of attracting the widest audience possible, we are committed to
distributing as much material as possible using the <quote
role="socalled">open source</quote> concept for computer software and a
similar policy for printed publications. This policy retains our copyrights
but allows you, with relatively few restrictions, to copy our materials
for your friends<!--, as long as you don't charge for the copies. We also ask
that recipients of copies register with us, so that we know who has our
materials. Such registration does not require contribution-->.</para>


<para>Certain materials that we publish contain information that we place
in the public domain. <emphasis role="bold">All language definition information is considered to
be public.</emphasis></para>


<!--<para>You can participate in the Lojban community at several levels of
activity, listed on the detachable registration form that accompanies this
brochure. It is entirely possible for you to participate in the community
without any expense, but we welcome contributions and donations to offset
our costs.</para>-->


<para>If you are attempting to learn the language, we provide as much help
as we can to assist you. We will put you in touch with
Lojbanists who might be interested in studying or communicating with you in
the language. You can also send your writings to us for review, or for
indirect exchange with others. We try to foster research and social
interaction among those who are learning, or who have already learned the
language. We aid such people in organizing, leading, and teaching formal
classes and study groups, and will sponsor affiliated groups in local areas
where non-profit sponsorship can be of benefit. We conduct an
annual (northern summer) celebration of the language and community, called
<quote role="socalled">Logfest</quote><indexterm id="idx70">
<primary>Logfest</primary>
</indexterm>, in conjunction with our annual
business meeting in the Washington DC area. We also expect to support other
local meetings and gatherings as the community grows.</para>


<para>Of course, we also try to publicize the language. Our representatives
can attend meetings to give presentations on the language. We distribute 
informational material, including these
brochures. Through our efforts, and with your help, the community of
Lojbanists is rapidly growing.<indexterm id="idx68" class="endofrange" startref="idx67" significance="preferred"/>
</para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>What can I do now?</para> </question>

<answer> <para>You can become involved in the Lojban project in a variety
of ways, depending on your background and interests, and on your available
time:</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>you can participate in completing the language
documentation;</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>you can devise applications for Lojban<indexterm id="idx55">
<primary>computer applications</primary>
</indexterm> in computers,
education, linguistics, and other fields;</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>you can help in organizing Lojbanists in your area, and in
recruiting new Lojbanists;</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>you can help in teaching the language to new people (even
while learning yourself);</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>you can assist in spreading Lojban to
non&ndash;English-speaking cultures by helping translate materials into
other languages, and by identifying, recruiting, and communicating with
contacts in other countries (international involvement is vital to ensuring
that Lojban remains culturally neutral);</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>you can contribute financially to support our organization,
its activities, and its publications;</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>you can use Lojban in composition, translation, and in
conversation with other Lojbanists.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>



<para>For many of these activities, you need to learn the language first.
However, even those who haven't yet had time to learn the language,
can assist in recruiting and
contributing ideas to the effort.</para>


<para>Helping to publicize the language, of course, does not take a lot of
time, or necessarily even knowing the language. Talk to friends, relatives
and colleagues. We will gladly provide copies of this brochure on
request. Lojban tends to sell itself; people who become informed are more often than not
intrigued by it.</para>


<para>Keep in touch with us. We want to know your ideas and opinions on the
language, on our various activities, and on our products. We welcome open
debate on the language design, and have even printed and made available
writings that are critical of various aspects of our efforts, when they are
of sufficient general interest. Open debate aids in understanding and
improves the overall quality of the language and of our presentation of it
to the world. We would rather hear criticism now within our friendly
community and either correct our problems or prepare an adequate response,
than to do so later when such issues are raised by outsiders.</para>


<para>In short, Lojban is a product of <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the community, including <emphasis>you</emphasis>
&mdash; if you choose.</para>


<para>Of course, the most important thing you can do is:</para>
<important><title>Use Lojban</title>


<para>Lojban will not really achieve the status of <quote
role="gloss">language</quote> until people <emphasis>use</emphasis> it. We
need creative people to write Lojban prose, poetry, and dialog. We need
translations made from fiction, technical literature, from religious and
philosophical writings, and from music. <emphasis>Only</emphasis> in this
way will Lojban be proven practical, and gain the credibility it needs to
succeed.</para> </important> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question>

<para>Who do I contact?</para> </question>

<answer> 

<para>We have several volunteers who serve to coordinate Lojban activities
in specific regions of the world. There is also a limited amount of Lojban
materials translated into languages other than English. This support is
constantly being added to; please contact us for details.</para>


<para>The Logical Language Group's website, which contains all its publicly
available information, is at: <informalexample><para><ulink
url="http://www.lojban.org"><computeroutput>http://www.lojban.org</computeroutput></ulink></para></informalexample></para>


<para>Two active Lojban-related mailing lists<indexterm id="idx71" significance="preferred">
<primary>Lojban mailing list</primary>
</indexterm> are available on the
Internet. <!--The mailing lists may be accessed at:
<informalexample><para><ulink
url="http://groups.yahoo.com"><computeroutput>http://groups.yahoo.com</computeroutput></ulink></para></informalexample>
Search for the keyword <quote role="gloss">lojban</quote>; t-->The general
Lojban list is called <computeroutput>lojban</computeroutput>, while the
list for discussions in Lojban only is
<computeroutput>jbosnu</computeroutput>. They may be accessed as follows:

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>Web</term><listitem><para><ulink
url="http://groups.yahoo.com/group/lojban"><computeroutput>http://groups.yahoo.com/group/lojban</computeroutput></ulink>,
<ulink
url="http://groups.yahoo.com/group/jbosnu"><computeroutput>http://groups.yahoo.com/group/jbosnu</computeroutput></ulink></para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Email</term><listitem><para><ulink
url="mailto://lojban@yahoogroups.com"><computeroutput>lojban@yahoogroups.com</computeroutput></ulink>,
<ulink
url="mailto://jbosnu@yahoogroups.com"><computeroutput>jbosnu@yahoogroups.com</computeroutput></ulink></para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Subscribe</term><listitem><para><ulink
url="mailto://lojban-subscribe@yahoogroups.com"><computeroutput>lojban-subscribe@yahoogroups.com</computeroutput></ulink>,
<ulink
url="mailto://jbosnu-subscribe@yahoogroups.com"><computeroutput>jbosnu-subscribe@yahoogroups.com</computeroutput></ulink></para></listitem></varlistentry>

</variablelist></para>


<para>If you have received a registration form and an order form with this
booklet, you can provide us with useful information to aid us in serving
you, and can order some of our materials. Write or call: 

<blockquote>
<address><firstname>Bob</firstname> <surname>LeChevalier</surname>
<affiliation><shortaffil>The Logical Language Group, Inc.</shortaffil></affiliation>
<street>2904 Beau Lane</street>
<city>Fairfax</city>, <state>VA</state> <postcode>22031</postcode>
<country>U.S.A.</country> 
<phone>(+1 703) 385-0273</phone> </address>
</blockquote>
E-mail can be sent to us at: <ulink
url="mailto://lojban@lojban.org"><computeroutput>lojban@lojban.org</computeroutput></ulink>
</para>

<blockquote><para><literallayout><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">e'osai ko sarji la lojban.</foreignphrase>
<wordasword>/eh-ho-sai, ko-SAHR-zhee, lah LOZH-bahn./</wordasword>
Please support Lojban! </literallayout></para></blockquote>

</answer> </qandaentry> </qandaset>
</chapter>
</part>



