<chapter id="lingissues"><title>Linguistic Issues of Lojban &mdash;
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">bauske se casnu pe le lojbo</foreignphrase>
</title><titleabbrev>Linguistic Issues of Lojban</titleabbrev>

<sect1 id="sw"><title>What is the Sapir&ndash;Whorf hypothesis?</title>

<para>The Sapir&ndash;Whorf hypothesis is the notion that the language you speak
affects the way you think. Most people who have learnt a foreign language,
or have grown up speaking two languages, will be familiar with this idea,
having found themselves thinking and speaking in one language or the other
because something is easier to say in that language. One of the main ideas
behind the Loglan/Lojban project was to create a language which is both
highly expressive and as culturally neutral as possible, then see what
people from different cultures do with it. To give an example, in most
European languages time and gender are very important &mdash; you can say
<quote>She goes</quote>, <quote>It went</quote>, <quote>He'll go</quote>
and so on, but just to say <quote>She/he/it go</quote>, with no particular
gender or time in mind, sounds strange. In Chinese, on the other hand,
<foreignphrase lang="zho">ta qu</foreignphrase> (<quote
role="gloss">he/she/it go</quote>) is perfectly normal. In Lojban there are plenty
of words to show the time of an action, its length, how it happens and so
on &mdash; but you don't have to use any of them. If you really wanted to,
you could say:

<informalexample>
<literallayout><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">le ninmu puzuze'udi'i klama</foreignphrase>
the female-human past-long-time-distance-long-time-interval-regularly go
<wordasword>A long time ago, for a long time, she went regularly.</wordasword></literallayout>
</informalexample>
But normally you'd just say:

<informalexample>
<literallayout><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">klama</foreignphrase>
[someone/something] go </literallayout>
</informalexample></para>

<para>Notice that you can translate the first example into English
(more-or-less) but the second one just won't go into English, or most
European languages. If you're European and this strikes you as odd, you
may have just witnessed a Sapir&ndash;Whorf effect! Understanding the potential
for Sapir&ndash;Whorf effects may lead to better inter-cultural understanding,
promoting communication and peace. </para>


<para>It is known that people's ideas and thought change somewhat when they
learn a foreign language. It is not known whether this change is due to
exposure to a different culture or even just getting outside of ones own
culture. It is also not known how much (if any) of the change is due to
the nature of the language, as opposed to the cultural associations. 
</para>


<para>The Sapir&ndash;Whorf hypothesis was important in linguistics in the 1950s,
but interest fell off partially because properly testing it was so
difficult. Lojban is a new approach to such testing. Obviously, if a
culture-independent language could be taught to groups of people, the
effects of language could more easily be separated from those of culture. 
</para>


<para>Unique features of Lojban remove constraints on language in the areas
of logic, ambiguity, and expressive power, opening up areas of thought that
have not been easily accessible by human language before. Meanwhile, the
formal rigidity of the language definition allows speakers to carefully
control their expressions (and perhaps therefore their thought processes). 
This gives some measure of predictive power that can be used in designing
and preparing for actual Sapir&ndash;Whorf experiments. </para>


<para>One of the prerequisites of a Sapir&ndash;Whorf experiment is an
international body of Lojban speakers. We need to be able to teach Lojban
to subjects who know only their native (non-English) tongue, and we need to
know in advance the difficulties that people from each language and culture
will have in learning Lojban. Thus, the Lojban community is actively
reaching out to speakers of languages other than English. </para>


<para>Lojban does not need to prove or disprove the Sapir&ndash;Whorf hypothesis
in order to be successful. However, if evidence is produced supporting the
Sapir&ndash;Whorf effect, Lojban will likely be perceived as an outstanding tool
of analytical and creative thought. </para> </sect1>

<sect1 id="use"><title>How can Lojban be used by scientists studying language? 
</title>

<para>An artificial language (AL) is a simple model of a natural language. 
It is used for communication like natural languages, simpler, more regular,
and relatively uncontaminated by culture effects. Unlike most natural
languages, an AL has not evolved through naturally processes of internal
change or contact with other languages. In addition, to the extent to
which details of an AL is pre-defined, the internal structure of the
language is far better known than that of any natural language. </para>


<para>Such a pre-definition, a language <quote role="socalled">prescription</quote>, makes an AL a
unique tool for studying the nature of language. As people learn the
language, the way they <quote role="socalled">acquire</quote> understanding of that prescription can
tell scientists how <quote role="socalled">natural</quote> the prescribed forms are. Actual usage of
the language can be compared to the prescription providing quantitative
data on specific patterns of usage. As the language evolves from its
relatively pristine initial state, it may start to deviate from its
prescription. Any such deviations will better inform researchers as to the
properties of a <quote role="socalled">natural</quote> language. The process of language change itself
will of course be open to investigation in a way never before possible. 
Finally, the existence of a relatively complete language prescription at
the birth of the language means that a <quote role="socalled">description</quote> of actual usage after
that initial state can be more simply created, maintained, and studied. 
</para>


<para>Lojban is undoubtedly the most carefully designed and defined AL ever
created. All aspects of its design have been carefully engineered by
several people encompassing expertise in a variety of disciplines,
including linguistics. The language prescription is similarly the most
complete of any language. As such, it serves as a unique basis for the
study of language usage and language change. </para>


<para>A new language like Lojban, with no native speakers, is termed a
<quote role="socalled">pidgin</quote>. As the language evolves, native speakers of other languages will
learn it, and will bring into their Lojban usage the perspective and
patterns of their native language. This interaction process, called
<quote role="socalled">creolization</quote>, affects all languages, and may be the principle cause of
language change. As Lojban is learned by speakers of a variety of natural
languages, this process can be studied directly in a way never before
possible, with the language prescription serving as a standard by which
deviations associated with speaker origin, and evolution of usage, can be
measured and described in detail. </para>


<para>An AL like Lojban has neither an associated <quote role="socalled">native accent</quote> nor a
culture base. Being much simpler and more regular than a natural language,
an adult speaker should acquire a fluency seldom achieved when studying a
natural language, and in a relatively short time. Lojban thus makes
possible relatively short-term studies of language learning and language
change. Processes that take generations in natural languages may be
observed in a few years in Lojban speakers. </para>


<para>With the learning of other languages acquiring critical importance in
today's international economy, Lojban provides a tool for researching in
language acquisition. Again, Lojban's simplicity allows the results of
such research to be obtained more quickly than in similar studies of
natural language acquisition. </para>


<para>No claim is made that studying Lojban will tell <quote role="socalled">all</quote> about language. 
While Lojban has already seen considerable communicative use, as far as the
rigorous standards of linguistics are concerned it will only be a <quote role="socalled">model</quote>
of a language at least for several decades, whose <quote role="socalled">naturalness</quote> will be
suspect. However, to the extent that Lojban serves the communicative and
expressive functions of human language, any theory about the nature of
human language must apply to Lojban. Language features and processes
identified in studying Lojban can then be confirmed in natural languages. 
Similarly, theories of the nature of language can be tested and refined
against this simpler model of a language before facing the more difficult
and time-consuming testing and analysis involved in natural language
research. </para>


<para>Because Lojban is relatively culture-free, and because of its
prescribed structure that is consistent with predicate logic, Lojban is an
ideal medium for the analysis and description of other languages. 
Currently, features in language must be compared against other natural
languages, and are usually described in scientific literature by glossed
translation into English. Lojban is simple and regular enough to be
acquired as a metalanguage for describing other languages; its structures
allow clearer reflection of the patterns of the language being described,
without interference from the competing patterns of English. </para>


<para>It is believed that, for anyone planning to later learn other
languages, the short time spent learning Lojban will be made up by the
reduced time needed later to learn those others. Studies in the 1930s, for
example, demonstrated that students could acquire greater skill in French
through one semester of Esperanto followed by one semester of French, than
they could by a full year course in French. Lojban offers similar
benefits, less likely to be limited to European languages. For example,
structures in Japanese that are difficult to explain in English because
they are so unlike English usage are much easier to explain using Lojban
patterns. Such study can be tied in with concepts of logic, and possibly
with computer-related activities, helping to show the essential
interrelated nature of language and other human endeavor. </para>


<para>Finally, Lojban's predicate grammar, makes it eminently suited for
ongoing computer research into natural languages. Lojban can be used for
parsing and analysis, as an internal medium of data storage, or as an
intermediate language for machine translation. Having a combination of
logical and natural language structures, Lojban combines the best of both
major structural approaches to language processing in computers. </para>


<para>The exercise of trying to invent a language can teach us things about
language that probably can't be learned in any other way. Even if Lojban
should fail as a language, we will learn. However, to the extent Lojban
succeeds, its potential as a basis for testing ideas about language, its
structure, and usage, is unlimited. The invention of Lojban is the
invention of the science of experimental linguistics. </para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="zwickycowan">
<sect1info><author><firstname>John</firstname> <surname>Cowan</surname></author></sect1info>

<title>Loglan and Lojban: A Linguist's Questions And An Amateur's 
Answers</title>


<para>The following questions about Loglan are based on a 1969 review by
Arnold M. Zwicky of James Cooke Brown's 1966 edition of <citetitle>Loglan
1</citetitle>. Although basically friendly, Zwicky's review raises a large
number of linguistic objections to Loglan as it existed in 1966. The review
represents the only formal notice the linguistics community has ever taken
of the Loglan Project. Unfortunately, the Project has never made any reply.
</para>

<para>The answers that appear here reflect the perspective of Lojban (not
Institute Loglan) as it exists in 1991. Therefore, no attempts have been
made to sort out Zwicky's misunderstandings of Brown's text, Brown's
misunderstandings (or mistakes in writing) about his own language, valid
points as of 1969 that were later changed by Brown, and valid points as
of 1969 that were changed when (or since) Lojban split from Institute
Loglan.</para>

<para>Throughout, <wordasword>Loglan</wordasword> refers to 1966 Loglan as
seen by Zwicky, and <wordasword>Lojban</wordasword> to current Lojban as
seen by me. The word <wordasword>Lojban</wordasword> is derived from the
same metaphor as <wordasword>Loglan</wordasword> (<quote>logical 
language</quote>) but using Lojban words
(<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">logji bangu</foreignphrase>).</para>

<para>As the title indicates, I (John Cowan) am only an amateur (lit. <quote 
role="gloss">lover</quote>) of
linguistics, and I may misinterpret some of Zwicky's points. The
question-and-answer format used here is purely for expository
convenience. Zwicky is not responsible for the form of the questions,
which reflect only my interpretations of his points, except for quoted
text within the questions followed by (Z), which are quotations from
Zwicky's original review. That review was published in 
<citetitle>Language</citetitle> 45:2
(1969), pp. 444&ndash;457.</para>

<qandaset>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>Lojban sentences do not have unique interpretations; how can Lojban
be said to be unambiguous?
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para>The sense in which Lojban is said to be unambiguous is not a simple
one, and some amplification of the fundamental claim is necessary.
Ambiguity is judged on four levels: the phonological&ndash;graphical, the
morphological, the syntactic, and the semantic.</para>

<para>Lojban is audio-visually isomorphic: the writing system has a
grapheme for every phoneme and vice versa, and there are no supra-segmental
phonemes (such as tones or pitch) which are not represented in the writing
system. Lojban's phonology contains significant pauses that affect word
boundaries, and allows pauses between any two words. The optional written
representation for pause is a period, although pauses can be unambiguously
identified in written text from the morphological rules alone. Lojban also
uses stress significantly, and again there is a written representation
(capitalization of the affected vowel or syllable), which is omitted in
most text, where the morphological default of penultimate stress
applies.</para>

<para>Lojban is morphologically unambiguous in two senses: a string of
phonemes (including explicit pause and stress information) can be broken
up into words in only one way, and each compound word can be converted to
and from an equivalent phrase in only one way.</para>

<para>The syntactic unambiguity of Lojban has been established by the use
of a LALR(1) parser generator which, in cooperation with a series of simple
pre-parser operations, produces a unique parse for every Lojban text. In
addition, the existence of a defined <quote role="socalled">phrase
structure rule</quote> grammar underlying the language (and tested via the
parser generator) guarantees that there are no sentences where distinct
deep structures generate isomorphic surface structures. On the other hand,
Lojban does have transformations, although they are not explicit in the
machine grammar: there are distinct surface structures which have the same
semantics, and therefore reflect the same underlying deep structure.</para>

<para>The claim for semantic unambiguity is a limited one only. Lojban
contains several constructs which are explicitly ambiguous semantically.
The most important of these are Lojban <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase>
(so-called <quote role="socalled">metaphors</quote>) and Lojban names.
Names are ambiguous in almost any language, and Lojban is no better; a name
simply must be resolved in context, and the only final authority for the
meaning of a name is the user of the name. <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase>
are further discussed in later replies. </para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>If the meaning of a particular
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> cannot be completely
understood from understanding the component parts, a separate dictionary
entry is needed for every possible <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase>,
making the Lojban dictionary infinitely long. How can this be avoided?
</para> </question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> are binary combinations of
predicates, such that the second predicate is the <quote 
role="socalled">head</quote> and the first
predicate is a modifier for that head. The meaning of the <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> is
the meaning of its head, with the additional information that there is some
unspecified relationship between the head and the modifier.</para>

<para><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> are the basis of compound
words in Lojban. However, a compound word has a single defined meaning
whereas the meaning of a <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> is explicitly ambiguous.
Lojban <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> are not as free as English
figures of speech; they are <quote role="socalled">analytic</quote>,
meaning that the components of the <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> do
not themselves assume a figurative sense. Only the connection between them
is unstated.</para>

<para>Most of the constructs of Lojban are semantically unambiguous, and
there are semantically unambiguous ways (such as with relative clauses) to
paraphrase the meaning of any <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase>. For example, <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">slasi mlatu</foreignphrase> (<quote
role="gloss">plastic-cat</quote>) might be paraphrased in ways that
translate to <quote role="gloss">cat that is made from plastic</quote> or
<quote role="gloss">cat which eats plastic</quote> or various other
interpretations, just as in English. However, the single (compound) word
derived from this <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase>, <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">slasymlatu</foreignphrase>, has exactly one meaning from
among the interpretations, which could be looked up in a dictionary (if
someone had found the word useful enough to formally submit it). There is
no law compelling the creation of such a word, however, and there is even
an <quote role="socalled">escape mechanism</quote> allowing a speaker to
indicate that a particular instance of a <quote
role="socalled">nonce</quote> compound word is <quote
role="socalled">nonstandard</quote> (has not been checked against a
dictionary or other standard), and may have a meaning based on an unusual
interpretation of the underlying <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase>. </para> </answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
The Loglan <quote role="socalled">primitive words</quote> seem to have been chosen at random,
without regard to any sort of semantic theory. Why was this done?
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>Lojban content words are built up from a list of about 1300 root
words (called <foreignphrase lang= "art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">gismu</emphasis></foreignphrase>), which are not necessarily to
be taken as semantically simple. Lojban does not claim to exhibit a
complete and comprehensive semantic theory which hierarchically partitions
the entire semantic space of human discourse.</para>

<para>Rather, the 1300-odd root words blanket semantic space, in the sense
that everything human beings talk about can be built up using appropriate
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase>. This claim is being tested in
actual usage, and root words can still be added if necessary (after careful
consideration) if genuine gaps are found. For the most part, the few gaps
which are now recognized (about 20 words have been added in the past
decade) reflect the completing of semantic sets. It is no longer permitted
for language users to create new <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">gismu</emphasis></foreignphrase> root words (in the standard
form of the language, at least); newly coined words must fall recognizably
outside the highly regulated <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">gismu</emphasis></foreignphrase> morphological space (a
specific and separate morphological structure is reserved for coined words
&mdash; usually borrowings &mdash; and a marker is available to indicate
that a word is a <quote role="socalled">nonce</quote> coinage rather than
an established <quote role="socalled">dictionary word</quote>).</para>

<para>Lojban's empirically derived word list is similar to that of Basic
English, which replaces the whole English vocabulary with English-normal
compounds built from about 800 root words. Lojban and Basic English both
allow for the adoption of technical terms from other languages to cover
things like plant and animal names, food names, and names of chemical
compounds.</para>

<para>The unfortunate terms <wordasword>primitive word</wordasword> and
<wordasword>prim</wordasword> formerly used by the Loglan Project suggested
the notion that Lojban's set of <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">gismu</emphasis></foreignphrase> was meant to be a list of
semantic primitives. This is not the case for Lojban, and the more neutral
term <wordasword>root word</wordasword> was adopted recently to reduce
confusion. Lojban predicate words, therefore, are now divided into
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">gismu</foreignphrase> <quote role="gloss">
root words</quote>, <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">lujvo</emphasis></foreignphrase> <quote role="gloss">compound
words</quote> and <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">fu'ivla</emphasis></foreignphrase> <quote
role="gloss">borrowings</quote> (lit. <quote role="gloss">copied
words</quote>). (Brown did originally select some words as <quote
role="socalled">semantic primitives</quote>; however, he later added words
with no claim that the additions were <quote
role="socalled">primitive</quote> in the same sense). </para> </answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>Some <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase>
seem poorly designed and not in keeping with expressed standards. Also,
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> like <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">nixli ckule</foreignphrase>, analogous to English
<wordasword>girls' school</wordasword>, are so open-ended in sense that
there is no way to block such far-fetched interpretations as <quote 
role="gloss">a school
intended to train girls between the ages of 6 and 10 to play the 
bassoon</quote>,
which is patently absurd. What is the proper interpretation of
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase>? </para> </question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>In the early part of the Loglan Project, poor <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase>
were regrettably common. In particular, it was common for <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> to
be calques on English expressions, such as <quote role="gloss">beautiful
type of small</quote> for English <wordasword>pretty small</wordasword>.
Many <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> employed the primitive for
<quote role="gloss">make</quote> (in the sense <quote role="gloss">make
from materials</quote>) where <quote role="gloss">cause</quote> would have
been more appropriate (e.g. <wordasword>kill</wordasword> = <quote
role="gloss">dead-make</quote>). Many years worth of effort since then have
gone into removing such <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">malglico</foreignphrase> (<quote
role="gloss">derogatively English</quote>) <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase>
from Lojban texts.</para>

<para>The Lojban <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">nixli ckule</foreignphrase> (<quote role="gloss">girl
type of school</quote>) cannot mean, out of context, <quote
role="gloss">school intended to train girls between 6 and 10 years of age
to play the bassoon</quote>, although if such a school existed it could
certainly be called a <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">nixli
ckule</foreignphrase>. This interpretation can be rejected as implausible
because it involves additional restrictive information. The undefined
relationship between <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">nixli</foreignphrase>
and <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ckule</foreignphrase> cannot drag in
additional information <quote role="socalled">by the hair</quote>, as it
were. Instead, this intricate interpretation would require a larger
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> incorporating <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">nixli ckule</foreignphrase> as one of its components, or
else a non-<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> construct, probably involving
a Lojban relative clause. As a comparision, such interpretations as <quote
role="gloss">school containing girls</quote>, <quote role="gloss">school whose
students are girls</quote>, and <quote role="gloss">school to train persons to
behave like girls</quote> are plausible with minimal context because these
renderings do not involve additional restriction. </para> </answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
Lojban claims to be unambiguous, but many constructs have vague
meanings, and the meanings of the primitives themselves are extremely
poorly specified. On the other hand, Lojban forces precision on speakers
where it is not wanted and where natural-language speakers can easily
avoid it. Is this appropriate to a culturally neutral, unambiguous
language?
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>Lojban's avoidance of ambiguity does not mean an avoidance of
vagueness. A Lojban aphorism states that the price of infinite precision
is infinite verbosity, as indeed Wilkins' <citetitle>Philosophical 
Language</citetitle>
illustrates. Lojban's allowable vagueness permits useful sentences to be
not much longer than their natural-language counterparts.</para>

<para>There are many ways to omit information in Lojban, and it is up to
the listener to reconstruct what was meant, just as in natural languages.
In each construct, there are specific required and optional components.
Unlike English, omitting an optional component explicitly and
unambiguously flags an ellipsis. Furthermore, the listener has a clear
way of querying any of this elliptically omitted information.</para>

<para>There are also some categories which are necessary in Lojban and not
in other languages. For example, Lojban requires the speaker, whenever
referring to objects, to specify whether the objects are considered as
individuals, as a mass, or as a (set theoretic) set. Likewise, logical
relations are made explicit: there can be no neutrality in Lojban about
inclusive vs. exclusive <wordasword>or</wordasword>, which are no more
closely related semantically than any other pair of logical
connectives.</para>

<para>These properties are a product of Lojban's fundamental design, which
was chosen to emphasize a highly distinctive and non-natural syntax (that
of formal first-order predicate logic) embedded in a language with the
same expressive power as natural languages. Through the appearance of
this one highly unusual feature, the intent of the Loglan Project has
been to maximize one difference between Lojban and natural languages
without compromising speakability and learnability. This difference
could then be tested by considering whether the use of first-order
predicate logic as a syntactic base aided fluent Lojban speakers in the
use of this logic as a reasoning tool.</para>

<para>As to the <quote role="socalled">primitives</quote>, Lojban
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">gismu</emphasis></foreignphrase> roots are defined rather
abstractly, in order to cover as large a segment of closely related
semantic space as possible. These broad (but not really vague) concepts can
then be restricted using <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> and other constructs to any
arbitrary degree necessary for clarity. Communicating the meaning of a
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis

role="term">gismu</emphasis></foreignphrase> (or any other Lojban word) is
a problem of teaching and lexicography. The concepts are defined as
predicate relationships among various arguments, and various experimental
approaches have been explored throughout the Loglan Project to determine
the best means to convey these meanings. It is believed that the current
working definitions of the <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">gismu</emphasis></foreignphrase> are much more clear than the
1966 set. </para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>On a more technical note, Lojban
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> involving more than two
components are always left-grouping (in the absence of a marker word).
Right-branching structure is <quote>much more natural to human
languages</quote> (Z). Why was this choice made? </para> </question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>Lojban is predominantly a left-branching language. By default, all
structures are left-branching, with right-branching available when marked
by a particle. Since the head of most constructs appears on the left,
left-branching structures tend to favor the speaker. Nothing spoken needs
to be revised to add more information. When the head is on the right, as in
the case of <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase>, left-branching may seem
counterintuitive, as it requires the listener to retain the entire
structure in mind until the head is found. However, left-branching was
retained even in <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> for the sake of
simplicity.</para>

<para>Experience has shown, however, that Lojban's left-branching
structure is not a major problem for language learners. Indeed, many
longer English metaphors translate directly into Lojban using simple
left-branching structures.
</para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
Loglan anaphora use a convention which is <quote>quite precise, and also
quite unlike anything in natural languages</quote> (Z), involving counting
backward from the reference to the referent. This provides unique
reference, but is also difficult to understand and use. Is there nothing
better that preserves the desirable property of unique reference which a
logical language needs?
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>The Lojban anaphora conventions have undergone much revision and
expansion since the early days of Loglan. There now exist both the <quote
role="socalled">traditional</quote> Loglan back-counting anaphora, which
refer to previous referents, and more <quote
role="socalled">natural-language&ndash;like</quote> anaphoric words which
are meaningless until assigned. Assignment may be either in afterthought or
forethought. These words are somewhat like natural language pronouns, but
may more closely be compared to the use of regions of space in American
Sign Language to refer to remote persons and things. Unassigned space
regions in ASL are similarly meaningless.</para>

<para>It is no longer a required convention that anaphora variables be
assigned in a fixed order. Subscripts (as in mathematics) are allowed
almost everywhere in the language, and provide for a countable infinity
of variables as of many other things. Lojban also has added the
capability of using individual letters and acronyms as anaphoric symbols.
</para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
Why does Loglan have a different and even more complex system of
<quote role="socalled">personal pronouns</quote> for speaker/listener reference? Is this level of
complexity really in order for what other languages treat as a simple
matter?
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>Lojban personal pronouns have been simplified. There are now forms
for I, II, III, I and II, I and III, II and III, and I and II and III.
There are no separate forms (and never have been) for plurals, because
number is not a mandatory grammatical category in any part of Lojban.
Number is expressed, when needed, using explicit numerals (which include
both precise and vague forms analogous to English
<wordasword>some</wordasword>, <wordasword>few</wordasword>,
<wordasword>too many</wordasword>, etc.) Honorifics have been added to the
language, using a general mechanism which may apply to any word or
construct, not merely to pronouns. </para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
Why does Loglan treat predicate connection as primary and sentence,
argument, etc. connection as secondary?
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>Whatever may have been assumed in the past for pedagogical purposes,
logical connection between sentences is basic to Lojban. All other forms
of logical connection may be transformed into equivalent sentence
connections.
</para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
Why are there so many structure words, and why are many of them so
similar? Wouldn't this make Loglan hard to understand at a cocktail
party (or a similar noisy environment)?
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>One of the recurrent difficulties with all forms of Loglan,
including Lojban, is the tendency to fill up the available space of
structure words, making words of similar function hard to distinguish in
noisy environments. The phonological revisions made when Lojban split
from Institute Loglan allowed for many more structure words (<foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">cmavo</emphasis></foreignphrase>), but
once again the list has almost entirely filled.</para>

<para>In some cases, notably the digits 0&ndash;9, an effort has been made
to separate them phonologically. The vocatives (including the words used
for communication protocol, e.g. over the radio) are also maximally
separated phonologically. Many other function words are based on shortened
forms of corresponding <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">gismu</emphasis></foreignphrase> roots, however, and are not
maximally separated.</para>

<para>A variety of ways to say <quote>Huh?</quote> have been added to the language,
partially alleviating the difficulty. These question words can be used
to specify the type of word that was expected, or the part of the
relationship that was not understood by the listener.
</para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>Loglan's <quote>restrictions on stresses
and pauses results in long sequences of unstressed syllables which must be
pronounced without a break</quote> (Z). This makes correct speech a
<quote>trial for a speaker of English or Russian, and not easy even for a
speaker of French</quote> (Z). Natural languages often have non-significant
pauses, but in Loglan every non-required pause is forbidden. Is Loglan
really speakable? </para> </question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>Lojban allows certain flexibilities of pause and stress in the area
of structure words. By default, all structure words are unstressed.
However, it is possible to set off structure words with optional pauses,
and even to give them optional stress, subject to a single limitation: a
structure word followed by a predicate word without pause must not be
stressed.</para>

<para>Pauses are now permitted between any two words; only within a word is
pause forbidden, and most words are short. <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">gismu</emphasis></foreignphrase>
and <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">cmavo</emphasis></foreignphrase> are always one or two
syllables long, and many <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">lujvo</emphasis></foreignphrase> compounds are only two or
three syllables. </para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>

<quote>A partial explanation for the existence of transformations is to be
found in the necessity for providing speakers of any language with
relatively acceptable variants of certain types of deep structures.</quote> (Z)
Loglan has no transformations, making some sentences expressible, but far
from straightforward or easy to use. Doesn't this make Loglan harder to
use than typical natural languages?
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>Lojban does have transformations, in the sense that there are
several alternative surface structures that have the same semantics and
therefore, presumably, the same deep structure. What it does not have is
identical surface structures with differing deep structures, so a
surface-structure&ndash;only grammar is sufficient to develop an adequate
parsing for every text. Knowledge of transformations is required only to
get the semantics right.
</para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>Lojban connectives cannot be used to
correctly translate English <wordasword>If you water it, it will
grow</wordasword>, because material implication is too weak and the special
causal connectives, which connect assertions, are too strong. What can be
done instead? </para> </question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>The English sentence <wordasword>If you water it, it will grow</wordasword> looks
superficially like a Lojban <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">na.a</foreignphrase> connection (material implication), but
it actually has causal connotations not present in <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">na.a</foreignphrase>. Therefore, a
proper translation must involve the notion of cause. Neither the Lojban
coordinating causal conjunction nor the two correlative subordinating
causal conjunctions (one of which subordinates the cause and the other
the effect) will serve, since these require that either the cause, or the
effect, or both be asserted. Instead, the correct translation of the
English involves <quote role="gloss">cause</quote> as a predicate, and might be paraphrased <quote>The
event of your watering it is a cause of the event of its future 
growing.</quote>
</para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
How can Loglan logical connectives be used in imperative sentences?
Logical connectives work properly only on complete sentences, and of
those, only those which actually assert something.
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>In early versions of Loglan, imperatives were marked by a predication
without a subject. In Lojban, there is a special imperative pronoun
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ko</foreignphrase>. This is a second
person pronoun logically equivalent to <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">do</foreignphrase>, the normal Lojban word for <quote 
role="gloss">you</quote>, but
conveying an imperative sense. Thus, an imperative can be understood as
commanding the listener to make the assertion true which results when
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ko</foreignphrase> is replaced by
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">do</foreignphrase>.</para>

<para>For example, <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ko
sisti</foreignphrase> (<quote role="gloss">Stop!</quote>) is logically
equivalent to <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">do sisti</foreignphrase>
(<quote role="gloss">you stop</quote>), and pragmatically may be understood
as <quote role="gloss">Make <quote><foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">do
sisti</foreignphrase></quote> true!</quote>. This allows logical connection to be
used in imperatives without loss of clarity or generality; the logical
connection applies to the assertion which is in effect embedded in the
imperative.</para>

<para>A minor advantage of this style of imperative is that tensed
imperatives like <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ko ba
klama</foreignphrase> (<quote role="gloss">Come in-the-future!</quote>) become
straightforward. </para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>Loglan's existential (bound) variables
appear to be non-standard. Brown states that the value of an existential
variable is always unknown to the speaker, rather than merely being
unspecified (perhaps for reasons of privacy or germaneness). Why is this?
Also, why isn't quantification over predicates provided? Why are the
back-counting anaphora unable to refer to existential variables? </para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>Existential variables are now interpreted in a standard way, to
refer to something unspecified, or something specified by a restrictive
relative clause (<quote>all x such that...</quote>). There are separate sets of
variables for quantifying over arguments and over predicates. In
general, the back-counting anaphora (which are less important in Lojban
than in Loglan) are not used to refer to other anaphoric words; this
makes the counting convention a bit more complex, but leads to more
generally useful results.
</para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
Untensed sentences ought to be neutral with respect to tense, mood,
and aspect, but Brown treats untensed sentences as expressing
disposition, habit, or ability &mdash; lasting throughout all time. This is
inconsistent with other parts of the language which treat ellipsized
material as merely unspecified.
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>The Lojban tense system has been greatly elaborated and clarified
with respect to its Loglan predecessor. There are now specific mechanisms
for stating the potentiality or actuality of a predication; in the absence
of these, a predication is neutral concerning the degree of actuality
expressed by it. It is no longer true that <quote 
role="socalled">untensed</quote>
predicates are used to express disposition or habit. They may be so used,
by ellipsis, but are in fact neutral in the absence of further
evidence.</para>

<para>Lojban tense, like other incidental modifiers of a predication, tend
to be contextually <quote role="socalled">sticky</quote>. When once
specified in connected discourse, to whatever degree of precision seems
appropriate, tense need not be respecified in each sentence. In narration,
this assumption is modified to the extent that each sentence is assumed to
refer to a slightly later time than the previous sentence, although with
explicit tense markers it is possible to tell a story in reversed or
scrambled time order. Therefore, each predication does have a tense, one
that is implicit if not necessarily explicit. </para> </answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
The decisions about the degrees of predicates (the number of
arguments expected for each) seem arbitrary. Color words are treated as
relations of degree 2; weather predicates which have no real subject
nevertheless need at least one argument; event predicates like <quote 
role="gloss">kiss</quote>
don't have an argument specifying the time. What theory underlies the
choice of place structures?
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>Very little. Place structures are empirically derived, like the
root word list itself, and present a far more difficult problem;
therefore, they will be standardized (if ever) only after everything else
is complete. Many of the particular objections made above have force,
and have already been accepted. There is no sufficiently complete and
general case theory that allows the construction of <foreignphrase 
lang="lat">a priori</foreignphrase> place
structures for the large variety of predicates that exist in the real
world.</para>

<para>The current place structures of Lojban represent a three-way
compromise: fewer places are easier to learn; more places make for more
concision (arguments not represented in the place structure may be added,
but must be marked with appropriate case tags); the presence of an argument
in the place structure makes a metaphysical claim that it is required for
the predication to be meaningful. This last point requires some
explanation. For example, the predicate <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">klama</foreignphrase> (<quote role="gloss">come,
go</quote>) has five places: the actor, the destination, the origin, the
route, and the means. Lojban therefore claims that anything not involving
these five notions (whether specified in a particular sentence or not) is
not an instance of <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">klama</foreignphrase>.
The predicate <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">cliva</foreignphrase>
(<quote role="gloss">leave</quote>) has the same places except for the
destination; it is not necesssary to be going anywhere in particular for
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">cliva</foreignphrase> to hold. <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">litru</foreignphrase> (<quote
role="gloss">travel</quote>) has neither origin nor destination, merely,
the actor, the route, and the means. The predicate <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">cadzu</foreignphrase> (<quote role="gloss">walk</quote>),
involves only a walker and a means of walking (typically legs). One may
walk without an origin or a destination (in circles, e.g.). For describing
the act of walking from somewhere to somewhere, the <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban"><emphasis role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase>
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">cadzu klama</foreignphrase> or the
corresponding <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">lujvo</emphasis></foreignphrase> <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">dzukla</foreignphrase> would be appropriate. The
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">tanru</emphasis></foreignphrase> <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">cadzu cliva</foreignphrase> and <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">cadzu litru</foreignphrase> may be similarly analyzed.
</para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
The Loglan phonological system is hard for English-speakers (to say
nothing of Japanese-speakers) to use, due to the large numbers of
consonant clusters and non-English diphthongs. How can a language be
appropriate as an international auxiliary language when it is difficult
to pronounce?
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>Lojban phonology is much better than 1966 Loglan's was. There are
now only 4 falling and 10 rising diphthongs, and the rising diphthongs
are used only in names and in paralinguistic grunts representing
emotions. All 25 vowel combinations are used, but they are separated by
a voiceless vocalic glide written with an apostrophe, thus preventing
diphthongization. English-speakers think of this glide as /h/, and even
speakers of languages like French, which has no /h/, can manage this
sound intervocalically.</para>

<para>Consonant clusters are controlled more carefully as well. Only 48
selected clusters are permitted initially; some of these, such as
<foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ml</foreignphrase> and <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mr</foreignphrase>, do not appear in English, but are
still possible to English- speakers with a bit of practice. Medial
consonant clusters are also restricted, to prevent mixed voiced&ndash;unvoiced
clusters, consecutive stops, and other hard-to-handle combinations. The new
Lojban sound /y/, IPA [&schwa;], is used to separate <quote
role="socalled">bad</quote> medial clusters wherever the morphology rules
would otherwise produce them.</para>

<para>Difficulties with the variety of permitted initial sounds are
overestimated. Lojban's morphology makes pronouncing these words easier
than they first appear. Initial consonant clusters occur only in content
words (predicates) and names. These words seldom are spoken in
isolation; rather, they are expressed in a speech stream with a rhythmic
stress pattern preceded (and followed) by words that end with a vowel.
The unambiguous morphology allows the words to be broken apart even if
run together at a very high speech rate. Meanwhile, though, the final
vowel of the preceding word serves to buffer the cluster, allowing it to
be pronounced as a much easier medial cluster. Thus <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">le mlatu</foreignphrase> (<quote 
role="socalled">the
cat</quote>), while officially pronounced /le,MLA,tu/, can be pronounced as
/lem,LA,tu/ with no confusion to the listener.</para>

<para>In addition, the buffering sound, IPA [&Iipa;] (the
<wordasword>i</wordasword> of English <wordasword>bit</wordasword>) is
explicitly reserved for insertion at any point into a Lojban word where the
speaker requires it for ease of pronunciation. The word <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">mlatu</foreignphrase> may be pronounced /m&Iipa;latu/ by
those who cannot manage <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">ml</foreignphrase>, and nothing else need be changed.
This sound is <quote role="socalled">stripped</quote> by the listener
before any further linguistic processing is done. </para> </answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
Loglan words resemble their English cognates, but unsystematically
so. Does this really aid learning, or does it make learning more
difficult?
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>Lojban words are less English-like than prior versions of Loglan,
since they were redone using newer (1985) data on numbers of speakers.
English is now less important in relative terms than Mandarin Chinese,
and most Lojban words are fairly equal mixtures of the two languages,
with lesser influences from Spanish, Hindi, Russian, and Arabic. The
other languages used in 1966 Loglan are no longer as prominent in terms
of world-wide number of speakers, and were dropped from the word-making
algorithm.</para>

<para>There is no proven claim that the Lojban word-making algorithm has
any meaningful correlation with learnability of the words. Brown has
reported that informal <quote role="socalled">engineering tests</quote>
were conducted early in the Loglan Project, leading to his selection of the
current algorithm, but these tests have never been documented or subjected
to review. The Logical Language Group has proposed formal tests of the
algorithm, and is instrumenting its software used for teaching vocabulary
to allow data to be gathered that will confirm or refute Brown's
hypothesis. Gathering this data may incidentally provide additional
insights into the vocabulary learning process, enabling Lojban to serve the
additional purpose of being a test bed for research in second language
acquisition.</para>

<para>In any event, the word-making algorithm used for Lojban has the clear
benefit of ensuring that phonemes occur in the language in rough proportion
to their occurence in the source natural languages, and in patterns and
orders that are similar to those in the source languages (thus the first
syllable of Lojban <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban"><emphasis
role="term">gismu</emphasis></foreignphrase> most frequently ends in /n/,
reflecting the high frequency of syllable ending /n/ in Chinese). The
result is a language that is much more pleasant-sounding than, for example,
randomly chosen phoneme strings, while having at least some arguable claim
to being free of the European cultural bias found in the roots of most
other constructed languages. </para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
Loglan has an absolutely fixed word order; in some cases, changes of
word order are possible, but only by the addition of marker particles.
Why is this? No natural language has an absolutely fixed word order (or
for that matter, an absolutely free one).
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>Lojban's word order is by no means fixed. In fact, Lojban is only
secondarily a <quote role="socalled">word order</quote> language at all.
Primarily, it is a particle language. Using a standard word order allows
many of the particles to be <quote role="socalled">elided</quote> (dropped)
in common cases. However, even the standard unmarked word order is by no
means fixed; the principal requirement is that at least one argument

precede the predicate, but it is perfectly all right for all of the
arguments to do so, leading to an SOV word order rather than the canonical
SVO (subject&ndash;verb&ndash;object). VSO order is expressible using only 1 particle.
In two-argument predicates, OSV, OVS, and VOS are also possible with only
one particle, and various even more scrambled orders (when more than
two-place predicates are involved) can also be achieved. </para> </answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>Loglan does not have WH-questions of the
English kind (its questions are fill-in-the-blank) and does not have
relative clauses. Therefore, no <quote role="socalled">unbounded</quote>
transformations (in the technical sense) exist in the language. Sentences
like <wordasword>I met a man that John said Mary told George to 
visit</wordasword> can be
translated only with great pain. How can such fairly common types of
constructions be represented better? </para> </question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>Lojban does have relative clauses, of the Hebrew type; the relative
marker and the relative pronoun are distinct. The marker <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">poi</foreignphrase> (or <foreignphrase
lang="art-lojban">noi</foreignphrase> for non-restrictive clauses) always
comes at the beginning, but the embedded clause is in normal order, using
the relative pronoun <foreignphrase lang="art-lojban">ke'a</foreignphrase>
at the appropriate location to represent whatever is being elaborated by
the clause. </para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry> <question> <para>If Loglan is to be used as an
international auxiliary language, it must be culturally neutral. But many
of its conceptual distinctions, for example the color set, are clearly
biased towards particular languages. There is a word for <quote
role="gloss">brown</quote>, which is a color not used in Chinese (although
a word exists, it is rare); on the other hand, there is only one word for
<quote role="gloss">blue</quote>, although Russian-speakers convey the
range of English <quote role="gloss">blue</quote> with two words. How can
Loglan be prevented from splintering into dialects which differ in such
points? </para> </question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>To some extent, such splitting is inevitable and already exists in
natural languages. Some English-speakers may use the color term <quote
role="gloss">aqua</quote> in their idiolect, whereas others lump that color with
<quote role="gloss">blue</quote>, and still others with <quote 
role="gloss">green</quote>. Understanding is
still possible, perhaps with some effort. The Lojban community will have to
work out such problems for itself; there are sufficent clarifying
mechanisms to resolve differences in idiolect or style between individuals.
The unambiguous syntax and other constraints defined in the language
prescription should make such differences much more easily resolvable than,
say, the differences between two dialects of English.</para>

<para>The prescriptive phase of Lojban is not intended to solve all
problems (especially all semantic problems) but merely to provide enough
structure to get a linguistic community started. After that, the language
will be allowed to evolve naturally, and will probably creolize a bit in
some cultures. Observing the creolization of such a highly prescribed
constructed language will undoubtedly reveal much about the nature of the
processes involved. </para> </answer> </qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
Loglan is supposed to be intended as a test of the Sapir&ndash;Whorf
hypothesis in its negative form: <quote>structural features of language make a
difference in our awareness of the relations between ideas</quote> (Brown). Is
this simply another way of saying <quote>Distinctions are more likely to be
noticed if structurally marked</quote> (Z)? If so, this is trivially true.
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>A better paraphrase might be <quote>Unmarked features are more likely to
be used, and therefore will tend to constitute the backgrounded features
of the language</quote>. By making the unmarked features those which are most
unlike natural-language features, a new set of thought habits will be
created (if Sapir&ndash;Whorf is true) which will be measurably different from
those possessed by non-Lojban speakers. If Sapir&ndash;Whorf is false, which
is the null hypothesis for Lojban purposes, no such distinctions in
thought habits will be detectable.</para>

<para>Further elaboration of Loglan Project thinking about Sapir&ndash;Whorf has
led to another alternate formulation: <quote>The constraints imposed by
structural features of language impose corresponding constraints on
thought patterns.</quote> In attempting to achieve cultural neutrality, Lojban
has been designed to minimize many structural constraints found in
natural languages (such as word order, and the structural distinctions
between noun, verb, and adjective). If Sapir&ndash;Whorf is true, there should
be measureable broadening in thought patterns (possibly showing up as
increased creativity or ability to see relationships between
superficially unlike concepts). Again, the null hypothesis is that no
measureable distinction will exist.
</para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>

<qandaentry>
<question>
<para>
How can <quote role="socalled">ease of thought</quote> be measured? Measuring facility with
predicate logic is not enough to establish <quote role="socalled">ease of thought</quote>.
</para>
</question>

<answer>
<para></para>

<para>Perhaps not. However, the Sapir&ndash;Whorf hypothesis tends to be
confirmed if experiments show that Lojban-speakers have a greater
facility with predicate logic than non&ndash;Lojban-speakers. That would
indicate that language (natural language) limits thought in ways that
Lojban-speakers can bypass. This form of test is not free of its own
difficulties, which have been discussed elsewhere.
</para>
</answer>
</qandaentry>

</qandaset>

<simplesect><title>Summary</title>

<para>Professor Zwicky's analysis raises several points of concern to
linguists who might be interested in the potential use of Lojban for
linguistic research. It is believed that sufficient planning and
linguistic understanding (and occasionally serendipity) has been
incorporated in the Lojban language design process to meet these
concerns. Other concerns no doubt exist; it is believed they can
similarly be addressed, and that Lojban will prove linguistically viable,
as well as useful in our attempts to understand language.
</para>

<para>
Meanwhile, as Lojban has evolved since the 1966 version of Loglan,
new features, not analyzed by Zwicky, have been added to the language,
further enhancing its potential value. These features, such as Lojban's
expression of the several varieties of natural language negation, the
system of attitudinal words for emotional expression, and the discursives
used for metalinguistic manipulation and comment on the discourse in
progress, raise new questions about the adequacy of Lojban's design,
while providing new opportunities for exploration of the properties of
natural language, as well as the correctness of the Sapir&ndash;Whorf
hypothesis.
</para>

<para>It is now time for linguists to again look at Lojban, with the
expectation that new questions, and new respect, will be forthcoming.
</para>
</simplesect>

</sect1>


</chapter>
